<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the transactions of the late King James in Ireland. Wherein is contain'd the Act of attainder past at Dublin in May, 1689. As also the proclamation for raising twenty thousand pounds per mensem, without an Act of Parliament. With other proclamations and acts made there.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B16635</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99883131</idno>
  <idno type="VID">201495</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240888671</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 11752648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide T.2030[11]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18993</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99883131</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99883131e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B16635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 201495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C25:1[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the transactions of the late King James in Ireland. Wherein is contain'd the Act of attainder past at Dublin in May, 1689. As also the proclamation for raising twenty thousand pounds per mensem, without an Act of Parliament. With other proclamations and acts made there.</title>
                  <author>James II, King of England, 1633-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavell, Jonathan Robinson, and Joseph Watts, booksellers in S. Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:201495:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF THE Transactions OF THE LATE KING JAMES IN IRELAND.</p>
            <p>Wherein is contain'd The Act of ATTAINDER Past at <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>May,</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO The Proclamation for Raising Twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Pounds <hi>per Mensem,</hi> without an Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>WITH Other Proclamations and Acts made There.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavell, Jonathan Robinson,</hi> and <hi>Joseph Watts,</hi> Booksellers in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:201495:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:201495:2"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF THE Transactions OF THE LATE KING JAMES IN IRELAND.</head>
            <p>SInce my repair into <hi>England,</hi> whither I in the Month of <hi>May</hi> last made my Escape with the manifest peril of my Life, being surrounded with a Thousand Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and Hazards, I encountred another Affliction of a different temper and complexion, and such as I little suspected to find among the Inhabitants of this happy Country. Had my Conversation been among <hi>Bigotted Papists</hi> (of whose Society I was never very fond); had I hapned into the Herd of desperate <hi>Malecontents,</hi> whose sordid
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:201495:3"/> complyance with the exorbitant Infractions of the Municipal Laws, and the arbitrary Invasions of all Civil Rights, during the despotical Tyranny of the late Reign had hardned them in their Apostacy, and rendred them as uncapable of Conviction, as they are unworthy of Mercy: I should either have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn my self from such unseasonable Picqueering, or with a Christian Compassion lamented their incorrigible Obstinacy and Defection. But sometime Business, sometime Curiosity leading me to a frequency of Converse, and a variety of New Faces, I became astonished to hear and observe many Persons (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi>) so shamefully abandon'd to a perverse and degenerate sense of the late miraculous Revolution, and an uneasie restlesness under the Auspicious Government of a <hi>Protestant King</hi> and <hi>Queen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when among their Sophistical Arguments I overheard them urge the Actions and Behaviour of the late King in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Tranquility of the <hi>Protestants</hi> there, and their Immunity from the Rigor of the Laws, and the Violence and Rapine of the Souldiers, as an invincible Proof of his Goodness and Moderation, and a demonstrative Induction to Cajole the good People of <hi>England</hi> into an Expectation of Peace and Felicity, by his Restitution to the Throne; my Admiration was turn'd into Extasie, and I became equally distorted with the emotions of Pity and Rage. And tho' I believe the number of those <hi>State Hereticks</hi> to be but inconsiderable, compared with the vast multitude of Persons well-affected to the present Government; yet I thought it my Duty to oppose these mistaken Principles, and (laying aside the consideration of all the Topicks drawn from the Doctrin of <hi>Non-Resistance, Passive Obedience,</hi> and such unpracticable Notions) to apply my self, as near as I can, to the Affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to endeavour to disabuse the World, and rectifie the erronious Apprehensions of such Men, as ignorantly applaud the Government and publick Managery of Matters in that most unfortunate Kingdom. In the Recounting whereof, it will be no presumption in me to bespeak an entire Credit to be given to what I shall hereafter relate; since the whole Narration shall be composed of such
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:201495:3"/> Particulars as are evidently deduc'd from Public <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations,</hi> or shall be justified against all Contradiction, by a positive avowing of what I have seen and heard.</p>
            <p>I shall begin where the <hi>Late King</hi> began at his first Arrival in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when to Ingratiate himself with the <hi>Protestants,</hi> and to beget an Opinion of his great Clemency among the People, he very graciously condescended to grant a General and <hi>Free Pardon</hi> to the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Bandon,</hi> amusing them with an assurance of an absolute Indemnity for their Transgressions; but soon after to gratifie the Malice of those Furious Zealots (who have plainly distracted that unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Prince) he remitted them to the severity of the Law, and expos'd them to a Trial for their Lives, upon which they were all found guilty of <hi>High Treason;</hi> and no other Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence could rationally be expected, when both <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Jury</hi> were composed of inexorable <hi>Papists;</hi> and in the mean time this mighty Crime, which was the Object of the Kings Mercy, and an Instance of the Cruelty and Injustice of his Subjects, was no more than that the Inhabitants of the Place observing their Neighbours to be openly <hi>Robb'd</hi> and <hi>Pillag'd,</hi> and clandestine Thievery to proceed to violent Depredation, they thought it prudent to shut their Gates, and avoid Plunder by a necessary Defence and Self-preservation. This was the first Essay of the gracious Indulgence of a <hi>Popish King</hi> to his <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Subjects.</hi> This was a plain Specimen of what is to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from him who will Mortgage his Reason to the humor of his <hi>Priests.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Business of Sir <hi>Thomas Southwell</hi> is altogether of another nature; and as the repetition of it may justly cause an abhorrence of those Blood-Suckers, who delight in the Torment and Ruine of such as they call <hi>Hereticks;</hi> so the Example may admonish all Men of Note and Degree, not to truckle their Authority in Vassalage to their Servants and Inferiours. The Earl of <hi>Seaforth</hi> taking a particular Fancy to Sir <hi>Thomas Southwell,</hi> a very hopeful young Gentleman (and under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for his reputed Rebellion) procur'd a Warrant from the Late King to Sir <hi>Richard Nagle</hi> his Attorney General, to pass a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:201495:4"/> Pardon for him, which the said Earl shewed to Sir <hi>Richard;</hi> but he in a most unmannerly and churlish fashion refused to obey it; saying, It was more than the King could do. The Earl returned to his Master, and reported the Answer of the Attorney General; who being sent for, own'd it to the King, and positively told him, It was not in his power to grant him a Pardon; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Poor Prince</hi> was overcome with Grief and Passion, and lock'd himself up in his Closet. This stiffness of the Surly Attorney General was grounded on the <hi>Act of Attainder,</hi> past in their Parliament, whereby that King is debar'd from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of Pardoning, and the Subject foreclosed from all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Mercy, as may be seen by the said Act hereafter in its due place. He who in <hi>England</hi> was flatter'd into a conceit of an absolute and unlimited Power to dispense with the Establish'd Laws, is not allowed in <hi>Ireland</hi> the Priviledge inherent to all Sovereign Powers by the Law of Nations, to pardon the Offences of a Subject. But even in this it has appeared (as by several other Instances) that he is permitted to pardon any Crime in a <hi>Roman Catholic;</hi> but in relation to a <hi>Protestant Heretick</hi> the Law is indispensible.</p>
            <p>And what Favour <hi>Protestants</hi> are to expect under a <hi>Popish King,</hi> and in a Kingdom where Popery is predominant, let all Men judge by their procedure in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where almost all the Churches (where the <hi>Irish</hi> Arms were prevalent) except in <hi>Dublin,</hi> were seised by Authority, the <hi>Protestant Ministers</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, and <hi>Popish Priests</hi> Setled and Inducted into Livings and Ecclesiastical Preferments. And that I may not be suspected to talk at Random, the Reader may for his further satisfaction peruse two several Acts past in their Parliament, whereby all Popish Priests and Dignitaries are vested in the perception of Tithes, and all other Ecclesiastical Dues: And tho' these Acts seem to have a direct aspect only on the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> yet they squint upon the <hi>Protestants,</hi> who having no Ministers of their own to whom they might pay their Tithes, would be obliged to pay the Tenth part to the Predominant Party, to whose arbitrary Power and Will the other Nine Parts are subjected. The Acts are as followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="act">
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:201495:4"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>An Act concerning</hi> Tithes, <hi>and other Ecclesiastical Duties.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHereas</hi> Tithes, Oblations, Obventions, Offerings, and other Ecclesiastical Duties and Profits growing and arising within all and every the respective Parish and Parishes of this Kingdom, (Impropriate Tithes excepted) have by the Law of the Land, and Constitution of Holy Church, ever since the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> been due and payable to the respective Pastors, Curates and Vicars of the said respective Parishes, having Cure of Souls therein; as a Provision and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for them for serving the said Cure, by celebrating Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service, Administring of Sacraments, Preaching and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structing the Parishioners thereof in the true Faith, and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other Pastoral Duties belonging to their Functions.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Forasmuch</hi> as the <hi>Roman Catholick Subjects</hi> of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for some time past have maintained their own Priests, Pastors, Curats and Vicars, and thereby have been very much impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished, by being obliged to pay their Tithes and other Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical Duties, to the Protestant Clergy, who have not laboured in the Administration of any of the said Spiritual Offices for any of the said Roman Catholicks.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Be it therefore Enacted,</hi> and it is hereby Enacted by your most Excellent Majesty, by and with the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by Authority of the same, That your Majesties <hi>Roman Catholick Subjects</hi> of this Kingdom, shall and may set out and pay all their Tithes, Oblations, Obven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other Ecclesiastical Duties (which of right are due and payable from henceforth to their respective Roman Catholick Priests, Pastors, Curats and Vicars, <hi>and to no other Person or Persons, of whatsoever Religion or Perswasion soever,</hi> (Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate Tithes excepted) any Law or Custom to the contrary notwithstanding.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:201495:5"/>
                           <hi>Provided always,</hi> and it is hereby further Enacted, That all and every Person and Persons of the said <hi>Roman Catholick Clergy,</hi> who shall be Entituled to any Tithes, or Payments in lieu of Tithes, by virtue of this Act, or otherwise, and their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Farmers, shall and may sue for the same, or the value thereof, by Writ, Bill, Petition, or Action of Debt, or such other Action for Substraction, or not setting forth the said Tithes in any of your Majesties Courts within this Kingdom, as heretofore they might have done, for detaining or not paying any Temporal Duty; and shall and may recover their Costs in such Suits, and <hi>all Incapacities</hi> heretofore devised by any Temporal Law, for disabling any of the said <hi>Roman Catholick Clergy</hi> from enjoying any Benefices or Tithes, or making any Collations or Benefices to them conferred, void, are hereby discharged and made void to all intents and purposes.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="act">
                        <head>Another Act concerning <hi>Appropriate Tithes,</hi> and other Duties payable to Ecclesiastical Dignitaries.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHereas</hi> by an Act past in this present Session of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Entituled, <hi>An Act concerning Tithes and other Ecclesiastical Duties,</hi> It is amongst other things Enacted, That the Roman Catholick Subjects of this Kingdom shall and may, for ever, pay their respective Tithes (Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate Tithes excepted) and their respective Oblations, Obven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other their Ecclesiastical Dues and Duties, to their respective Roman Catholick Priests and Pastors, Curates and Vicars; to whom also Remedy is given by the said Act for recovering the same.</p>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:201495:5"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And whereas</hi> within this Kingdom there are several Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate Tithes formerly belonging to Archbishops, Bishops, Deans, Deans and Chapter, Collegiate Churches, Arch-Deacons, Prebends, and other Ecclesiastical Dignitaries: And whereas a Doubt did arise, Whether the Roman Catholicks, who are to pay such Appropriate Tithes, are by the said Act to pay the same to their respective Roman Catholick Priests, Pastors, Curates and Vicars, who are Incumbents within the respective Parishes where such Appropriate Tithes are due, to the respective Roman Catholick Dignitaries, within such Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes or Places were such Tithes are payable.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And it is hereby</hi> Declared and Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by Authority of the same, That the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> of this Kingdom, who are to pay any such Appropriate Tithes, shall from time to time, and at all times hereafter, for ever, pay the same to the respective Roman Catholick Archbishops, Bishops, Deans, Deans and Chapter, Collegiate Churches, Archdeacons, Prebends, or other Roman Catholick Dignitaries, that are or shall be Roman Catholick Dignitaries, within the Parishes or Places where such Tithes are or shall be payable in such manner as the same were formerly paid since the Reformation, to the respective Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Archbishops, Bishops, Deans, Deans and Chapter, Collegiate Churches, Archdeacons, Prebends, or other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical Protestant Dignitaries of such Parishes or Places: And that the said respective Roman Catholick Archbishops, Bishops, Deans, Deans and Chapter, Collegiate Churches, Archdeacons, Prebends, and other Roman Catholick Dignitaries, shall have the same, or the like Remedy, for the respective Recovery of such Appropriate Tithes, as the said respective Roman Catholick Priests, Pastors, Curates and Vicars, have or shall have, for the recovery of the Tithes, payable to them respectively by virtue of the said former Act, any thing in the said former Act to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:201495:6"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And whereas</hi> it may be a Doubt, who shall be deemed, taken or reputed to be Roman Catholick Archbishops, Bishops, Deans, Archdeacons, or other Roman Catholick Dignitaries, Priests, Pastors, Curates and Vicars, within the meaning of this, or the said former Act. <hi>Be</hi> it hereby Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That such Roman Catholick Archbishops, Bishops, and Deans, now in being, as His Majesty by any Instrument under his Privy Signet and Sign Manual, shall signifie to be Roman Catholick Archbishops, or Bishops of any Diocess, or Deans of such Places or Churches within this Realm, shall be reputed, taken and deemed the respective Roman Catholick Archbishops and Bishops of such Diocess, and Deans of such Places within this Realm: And that such Person and Persons as hereafter shall be Roman Catholick Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops, or Bishops of any Diocess within this Kingdom, or Dean of any Place or Church, shall be such, and no other, as shall be respectively Ordained Archbishops, or Bishops of such Diocess, or Deans of such Places or Churches, by the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or Presentation of His Majesty, his Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors; and that such shall be deemed Roman Catholick Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, Prebends, or other Roman Catholick Dignitaries; and such shall be deemed Roman Catholick Priests, Pastors, Curates and Vicars, as have been, or shall be allowed and approved of by the Roman Catholick Archbishop of the Diocess, where he or they did or shall Officiate, or they respectively shall be approved of, or allowed by the Roman Catholick Metropolitan of the Province where such Diocess doth lie, in case there was, or there is, or there shall be no Roman Catholick Bishop in being, of such Diocess, at the time of such allowance or approbation.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And be it further Enacted,</hi> That the King's Majesty, his Heirs and Successors, and all such as are, or shall be Roman Catholick Archbishops, Bishops, or other Roman Catholick Dignitaries within this Kingdom, and their Successors; and all Roman Catholick Lords, Knights, Gentlemen, or others, and their Heirs and Assigns respectively, who have, or shall have any Advowson, Collation, or Right of Presentation, Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:201495:6"/> or Collation to any Benifice within the Realm, shall for ever hereafter upon vacancy of any such Benifice, have full Power and Authority to present or Collate a fit Person, to be the Roman Catholick Dignitary, Curate, Vicar, or Pastor of such Benifice, in such manner and form as they respectively, or any of their Predecessors, or Ancestors, did or could have lawfully done.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And be it further Enacted,</hi> That so much of any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute as tends to disable, or incapacitate any of the said Roman Catholick Archbishops, Bishops, Deans, Deacons, Archdeacons, Prebends, or any other Roman Catholick Dignitaries, Priests, Pastors, or Vicars of the Roman Catholick Church, from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, having, holding, or enjoying any of the said Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical Dignites, or livings, in manner aforesaid, be and is hereby repealed and made void.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>It is a matter not unworthy the observation, how dexterously the Government there could prevaricate in their dealings with the poor enslaved <hi>Protestants.</hi> For upon any apprehension of Succors arriving from <hi>England,</hi> or other pretext to fleece and squeeze them, an Information was presently given, how numerous the <hi>Protestants</hi> were, and what danger may arise from thence; and then they were fortwith confined, and hurried away to Prison, and their Houses and Goods exposed to the Rapine of the <hi>Irish</hi> and <hi>French:</hi> At another time, when it might be subser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to their designs, to lessen their number and undervalue the strength of the <hi>Protestants;</hi> then they give out that their number was but small, and their Interest inconsiderable: And this is very remarkable in a late passage at the City of <hi>Limer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick,</hi> where the Cabal of the Papists projecting to get the the Churches (there) into their Hands, Represented to the King and Council, that the <hi>Protestants</hi> in that place were so very few, that there was no need to assign them any more, than one Church for their meeting; and this Suggestion was fortified by a Letter from the Earl of <hi>Limerick</hi> attesting the same; but when the business came to be examined, it appeared
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:201495:7"/> to be so gross and palpable a Delusion, that their King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self saw through it, and discovered the Imposture; and out of meer shame dismist the Petitioners without any success in their Application.</p>
            <p>If at any time, an Information was given to the Government of any Mony or Plate, or other things valuable in the Hands of a <hi>Protestant,</hi> thô guarded by the solemnity of a Protection; this was soon seconded by the suspicion of some <hi>Plot</hi> against the Government, and immediatly a Party was sent to seise their Persons, to Search, and Plunder their Houses; and so after the Infliction of all sorts of Misery and Distress, they are admitted to Liberty, under the Caution of Bonds for Good behaviour, but nothing left to sustain them, or to prevent the Calamitous Assaults of Poverty and Famin.</p>
            <p>At another time they proceded with a more Jesuitical Fineness, for having in their Eye a concealed purchase of Mony, or good Movables, in the Hands of a <hi>Protestant;</hi> immediatly an Order was secretly granted, to seise the Person and secure <hi>the Goods:</hi> and then to amuse the World with an Opinion of their Justice and Lenity, a <hi>Proclamation</hi> was conceived with a plausi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Promise of Indemnity, to all <hi>Protestants</hi> under their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection; and an invitation to all Men, to rest secure under the Benignity of it. But in the mean time the matter is so Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the <hi>Proclamation</hi> shall not be published, nor deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Sheriffs Hands, or other Officers, thô Antidated before the Issuing such Order, till a certain Advertisement be received, that the Order is Executed, and the work done.</p>
            <p>What a miserable and an inexampled Oppression is it, that the poor Subjects shall be compelled to part with their Goods and Merchandise for a contemptible <hi>Lump of Brass,</hi> or <hi>Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter!</hi> Yet such is, and hath been the constant proceeding of the late <hi>King</hi> towards his Subjects of <hi>Ireland;</hi> whose Goods and Commodities he rather seiseth than buyeth, and becoming the grand Merchant of the Kingdom, he is the general ingrosser of all Trade, which he vents and exports to his dear <hi>Corres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondent in France;</hi> Bargaing with the Owner at such a Rate, as the Buyer is pleased to make, and discharging his Contract in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:201495:7"/> Bits of <hi>Copper, Pewter</hi> and <hi>Brass;</hi> which can in no way avail the poor Seller, or support him in the Circulation of his Trade. I will only present the Reader with one Instance, and give him an Authentick account of what Goods were taken up in <hi>Dublin</hi> at one time for the King'<hi>s</hi> use, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) were seized by <hi>Armed force,</hi> and a Price set upon them, at the Pleasure of the taker.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Seized in the City of</hi> Dublin <hi>for the Kings use,</hi> February <hi>the</hi> 6th, 1689.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Tann'd hides.</cell>
                     <cell>Raw-hides▪</cell>
                     <cell>Stones of Wool at 18 <hi>lb.</hi> in the Stone</cell>
                     <cell>Tuns of Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</cell>
                     <cell>Tones of But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In <hi>Oxmantown</hi>—</cell>
                     <cell>00920</cell>
                     <cell>02140</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>S. <hi>Andrews,</hi> S. <hi>Peters,</hi> and S. <hi>Brides</hi>——</cell>
                     <cell>01161</cell>
                     <cell>—2190</cell>
                     <cell>61105</cell>
                     <cell>389</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>S. <hi>Catherins,</hi> S. <hi>James,</hi> and S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> without—</cell>
                     <cell>05071</cell>
                     <cell>—3192</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Within the City—</cell>
                     <cell>11619</cell>
                     <cell>—7192</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>18771</cell>
                     <cell>14687</cell>
                     <cell>61105</cell>
                     <cell>389</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>This with much more, (about the time Sr. <hi>Cloudsly Showell</hi> stood before <hi>Dublin</hi>) was a carrying on Board the Ships that lay in the Harbour, to be transported for <hi>France;</hi> which for that small time, Sir <hi>Cloudsly Showell</hi> tarried there, had some Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission; but as soon as he was gon, the same, and many more Hands were employed, that all might be sent off; whilst the like Methods were a putting in Execution, in all parts of the Country, Seizing and Carrying away, what the <hi>Protestants</hi> had, in Order to be sent after the former, by the next opportunity: which without doubt has not been neglected, since met with no opposition for several Months thereafter; Beggering the Inhabitants, and Impoverishing the Kingdom, by a wilful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vastation of those Staple Commodities, for which no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn could be expected, (none else being promised) but mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials to Murder the remainder of the poor unhappy <hi>Protestants</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:201495:8"/> under their Government, and to annoy those that were not; whereas these Commodities at other times, by the Circulation of Trade in these Kingdoms, brought welcome exchanges of Gold and Silver, to the Merchants and other dealers in <hi>Ireland;</hi> who freely distributed the same among all the other Inhabitants for their benefit, and the advancement of Trade, which being now stopt, and those Commodities sent to strengthen our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; what damage and Loss this has been and may be to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as well as to the other Dominions, under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Majesties, Ile not take upon me to Compute.</p>
            <p>The Country being well Stored with Grane of all Sorts, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the Counties about <hi>Dublin,</hi> whereof the generality of the Inhabitants are <hi>Protestants,</hi> a very plausible <hi>Proclamation</hi> was Issued out to encourage the Farmers, to supply and furnish the Markets; which when they had for some time frequented, another <hi>Proclamation</hi> came forth, setting a precise Rate (but much lower than the Common Market price,) upon all kinds of Grane, Provisions, and other Merchantable Commodities, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straining the Seller to part with his Goods at the Rates pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, on pain of losing all without a satisfaction; or inplain English, to Seize on Mens properties and effects under pretence and colour of <hi>furnishing the Kings Stores:</hi> See the <hi>Proclamation,</hi> which was first published on a certain Market day, when (by the encouragement the Farmers had from a <hi>Proclamation</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished some short time before, for setting higher Rates on all Commodities,) it was observed the Markets in all parts of the City, had more Corn in them than had been seen for some Months before; the Lord Mayor by name <hi>Mac Dermot,</hi> some daies before went into the Market, and told the Country People and Farmers, that the reason of the precedent <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> was only to supply the King, with what he wanted for his own necessary occasion, and that if they would bring in plenty of Corn, that the King might take off the best, the rest they might sell at the best and greatest prices they could; by which the Markets being very full, the said Lord Mayor with his Officers came into the Market, and Seized all, at what prices he pleased; part whereof he sent to the Kings use, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:201495:8"/> rest he disposed as he thought fit, and was highly pleased with the trick; after which there was not seen five Barrels on a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket day.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="proclamation">
                        <head>By the King a Proclamation.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <signed>James R.</signed>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WHereas we are informed, That the Price of Corn, Meal, Wool, Leather, and other Commodities is so high, that the Persons employed by us to make Stores and Magazines of Grain, and to provide Cloaths and other Necessaries for our Troops, cannot Buy the same but at excessive Rates, though we are well assured there are great quantities of all sorts of Grain, Wool, Leather, and other Commodities within this our Kingdom; and having on the one hand considered the absolute necessity of making Magazines and Stores of Grain and Meal for the support of our Army, and of providing Cloaths and other Necessaries for our Troops; And on the other hand, at what Rate the Farmers, Husbandmen, and other Dealers and Traders may sell the same to discharge their Rents, Subsidies, and other Incumbrances, reserving a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency for the use of their Families, and a sufficient proportion of Seed for Tillage: We have thought fit by the Advice of our Privy Council, to set a Rate upon such Corn, Meal, Wool, Leather, and other Commodities as shall be bought for our use. We do therefore by the Advice aforesaid, strictly Charge and Command all Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Husbandmen, and others, who have any Wheat,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:201495:9"/> Bear, Barley, Meslin, Oats, or Oatmeal, that they dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of the same, or so much thereof as we shall think fit to make use of, at the Rates following; That is to say, <hi>20s.</hi> the Barrel of the best Wheat, <hi>18s.</hi> the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of ordinary Wheat, <hi>15s.</hi> the Barrel of Meslin, <hi>12s.</hi> the Barrel of the best Bear, <hi>11s.</hi> the Barrel of ordinary Bear, <hi>13s.</hi> the Barrel of the best Malt, and <hi>12s.</hi> the Barrel of ordinary Malt, 14s. the Barrel of good Barley, and <hi>6s.</hi> the Barrel of good Oats, in the Counties of <hi>Dublin,</hi> City of <hi>Dublin, Meath, West▪ Meath, Wicklow,</hi> and <hi>Kildare;</hi> and <hi>15s.</hi> the Barrel of the best Wheat, <hi>13s.</hi> the Barrel of ordinary Wheat, <hi>11s.</hi> the Barrel of the best Bear, <hi>10s.</hi> the Barrel of Ordinary Bear, <hi>12s.</hi> the Barrel of the best Malt, <hi>11s.</hi> the Barrel of ordinary Malt, <hi>12s.</hi> the Barrel of good Barley, <hi>4s.</hi> the Barrel of good Oats, and <hi>12s.</hi> the Barrel of good Oatmeal, in all other parts of the Kingdom, the said Barrel to be <hi>Bristol</hi> Measure, and the said respective Rates to be paid upon the delivery of the said Corn and Meal at our Store next the place where the Corn or Meal lies. And in case the Farmers, Husbandmen, and others that have such Corn or Meal to sell, shall refuse to bring the same to our Stores at the Rates aforesaid, at the Request of the Commissioner-General of our Provisions and Stores, or of our Commissaries of Bread, or his or their Deputies or Agents, We do hereby strictly Charge and Command our respective Lieutenants, Deputy-Lieutenants, and Sheriffs of our Counties of this our Kingdom, that they or any of them do immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the said Farmers, Husbandmen, and others, to Thresh and prepare their said Corn and Meal, and to bring the same to our Stores, or such proportion thereof as shall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:201495:9"/> be thought necessary for our Service, at the Rates afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said; in which Case our said Lieutenants, Deputy-Lieutenants, and Sheriffs, our said Commissioner General of our Provisions and Stores, our Commissaries of Bread, his and their Deputies and Agents are to take special Care, that the said Farmers, Husbandmen and others, having such Corn and Meal be permitted to keep suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent proportion thereof for the Subsistence of them and their Families, with sufficient quantity of Barley and Oats for Tillage, as aforesaid. And we do further strictly Charge and Command our said Commissioner-General of our Provisions and Stores, our Commissaries of Bread, his or their Deputies or Agents, upon the delivery of any such Corn or Meal into any of our Stores, that they thereupon pay down to the Owners of such Corn and Meal according to the Rates aforesaid. And we do further require our said Commissioner General of our Provisions, to appoint several Store-houses in such Places as may lie convenient for such Farmers, Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen and others, to carry such Corn or Meal to our Stores, as aforesaid. And we do further, by the Advice of our Privy Council, strictly Charge and Command all such as have any store of Wool, Leather, Tallow, or salted Hides, that they dispose of so much thereof for our use, as we shall have occasion for, at the Rates following; That is to say, Good Merchantable Wool <hi>10s.</hi> the Stone, (<hi>18 lb.</hi> to the Stone), and for good Merchantable Tann'd Leather, <hi>7d.</hi> the Pound Sole-Leather, and <hi>6d.</hi> the Pound Ʋpper Leather; for Tallow, <hi>30s.</hi> the Hundred Weight, and for large Ox-Hides salted, <hi>20s.</hi> the Hundred Weight; And in case the Owners of such Wool, Leather, Tallow or Hides, shall refuse to supply our Occasions at the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:201495:10"/> Rates aforesaid, We do hereby declare, That we will give Directions to the Commissioners of our Treasury, to cause so much of the said Wool, Leather, Tallow and Hides to be seized upon for our use at the Rates aforesaid, as we shall have occasion for.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given at our Court at <hi>Dublin-Castle,</hi>
                              <date>the 28th of <hi>February,</hi> 1689.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>After the Late <hi>King</hi> was obliged by his necessity to make <hi>Brass-Money</hi> current in <hi>Ireland,</hi> it was at first pretended to pass only in Payments between Man and Man in their daily Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and Dealings, and in publick payment of Duties to the <hi>Exchequer.</hi> But soon after the <hi>Irish</hi> beginning to consider, that they were generally Indebted to the <hi>English,</hi> and that this might be a fit season, and a lucky opportunity to get their Debts easily and cheaply discharged, a Proclamation was published, enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and requiring, That <hi>Copper and Brass-Money should pass as Current Money within the Realm of</hi> Ireland, <hi>in the payment of Bills, Bonds, Debts by Record, Mortgages, and all other Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatsoever.</hi> By which Knack many a poor <hi>Protestant</hi> was Fob'd out of his Right, and compell'd to take an Heap of Trash for his Debt, (as he was for his Wheat and other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities) or be precluded from any further satisfaction.</p>
            <p>And thus I have heard that Colonel <hi>Roger Moore</hi> was serv'd, (but I do not aver it upon my certain knowledge) who having an Incumbrance of 3000 <hi>l.</hi> upon the Lord <hi>Dillon</hi>'s Estate, who is married to the Daughter of the Lord or Lady <hi>Tyrconnel;</hi> she sent for him, and told him, That having some Money at her command, and being very desirous to take off the burthen from her Daughters Estate, she was content to pay him off in Ready-Money, provided he would make some handsom abatement of the Sum due. The Gentleman being Complaisant to the Lady, and very willing to receive Money in such a time of Scarcity, freely consented to abate a Thousand Pounds, so the rest might
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:201495:10"/> be paid down at once: The Lady seem'd very thankful, and appointed him to come next day, and to bring the Deeds and Obligations with him, and to receive his Money. Accordingly he came, and having given a legal Release, the Lady open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Door, and shewed him a long Table, covered over with <hi>Copper</hi> and <hi>Brass,</hi> and tendered it for his payment: which whether he rejected in Passion, or hired a Cart to carry it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, I cannot tell; but this I can say, having an Estate which was Mortgaged to the old Proprietor, before 1641. to which on Payment of the Mortgage Mony, he hoped to be restored by Repealing the <hi>Acts of Settlement;</hi> he repaird to me, and desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, to appoint time and place for Paying the Mortgage Mony, of which I have taken time to consider. One of the most Eminent Silver Smiths in <hi>Dublin,</hi> having sold all his Plate to a <hi>Papist,</hi> who promised to pay him his price (agreed upon) in Silver and Gold; but no Faith being to be kept with <hi>Hereticks,</hi> the Gold-Smith was compeld to take <hi>Brass</hi> and <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi> But not to detain the Reader with many more of these Examples, I here present you with that Savory and Fruitful <hi>Proclamation:</hi> Which is, to make <hi>Brass Mony</hi> pass in Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all Debts.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="proclamation">
                        <head>By the King a Proclamation.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <signed>James R.</signed>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WHereas, We have by former Proclamations of the <hi>18th &amp; 27th</hi> Days of <hi>June</hi> last, for the Reasons therein set forth; Ordained and Declared, that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Coyn made by our Order of a certain Metal, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Copper</hi> and <hi>Brass,</hi> and Marked and Stamped as in the said Proclamations is expressed in Sixpence,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:201495:11"/> Twelvepence, and half Crown pieces, should during our Pleasure pass as Current Mony, among all our Subjects within this Realm, according to the Rates and Values in the said Proclamations mention'd; and in all Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to be paid either to us or from us, or to, or by any of our Subjects within this Kingdom; excepting Mortga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges▪ Bills, Bonds, or Obligations, Debts due by Record, and Mony heretofore left in Trust or keeping with any Person. And whereas it hath been since represented to us, that such restriction upon the said Coyn, is a great hindrance to Trade and Industry, and to the Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the said Mony, in regard Men of Trade and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry cannot have Credit, without passing Bonds and Judgments, which since they cannot satifie by the said Mony▪ they are therefore the less industrious, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it by the Sale of any of their Goods or Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, as are also the generality of all others; because when they have acquired any quantity thereof, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thereby pay their Debts, nor clear their Estates from Incumbrances; wherefore We have thought fit by the Advice of our Privy Council, further to Declare and Ordain, that the aforesaid Mony, made of Mixture of <hi>Copper</hi> and <hi>Brass</hi> as aforesaid, shall hereafter dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Pleasure pass as Current Mony within this Realm, not only in all Payments, in the said former Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions mentioned; but also in all the said Payments of Bills, Bonds, Debts by Record, Mortgages, and all other Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatsoever, in the said former Proclamations excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And whereas this is Ordered at this time to supply the present scarcity of Mony, and remedy the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies which would otherwise ensue; We do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hereby Promise and Declare to all our loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:201495:11"/> that as soon as the said Mony shall be called in, and Decried, We shall thereupon not only receive from all our Loving Subjects within this Kingdom, such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion thereof, as shall be in any of their Hands, at such time as it shall be so Decried, according to the Value for which it now passes, in satisfaction of any Rents, Customs, Excise, Debts or Duties, which they shall owe to us; but also where no such Debts or Duties shall be due to us, we will make full Satisfaction for the same in Gold, or Silver of the Current Coyn of this Kingdom.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given at our Court at <hi>Dublin-Castle,</hi>
                              <date>the 4th Day of <hi>February</hi> 1689.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Of late they are grown so severe to the poor Protestants, that they will not suffer them to buy a loaf of Bread from a Baker, but at the Second hand from the Souldiers, and are forced to pay a treble Rate for it, and even that Liberty is now restrained, since the <hi>French</hi> are Garisoned in <hi>Dublin,</hi> so that we may too sadly expect to hear that many of them are Starved in the Streets.</p>
            <p>But I challenge all History and Records of Nations, to Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel the late shameful usage of the poor <hi>Protestant Prisoners in Galway,</hi> upon whom was placed so Odious a Cheat, so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-like a Sham, that posterity will hardly be induced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; and I must Implore the Charity of the present Age, not to look upon it as a fable: but it is so certain and so sad a truth, that I defie the Subtilty and Impudence of a <hi>Jesuit,</hi> to gainsay or contradict it. There was a Stipulation made not long since, between the Late <hi>King James</hi> and the <hi>French Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> to Exchange some Regiments of Auxiliaries, and about Five Thousand Men being accordingly sent from <hi>France</hi> and Landed in <hi>ireland,</hi> the Late <hi>King James</hi> ordered the like
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:201495:12"/> Number of <hi>Irish</hi> to be forthwith Embarked, and Transported into <hi>France,</hi> under the Conduct of <hi>Major General Mac Carty,</hi> (under whom they would do great Feats, as by Experience against the <hi>Inis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killin</hi> Men,) among whom the Regiment under the Command of Colonel <hi>Robert Fielding,</hi> alias <hi>Hansom Fielding,</hi> was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be one; but before he could get his Regiment on Board, a great Number of the Men Run away, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their natural, and usual custom; so that he became mightily puzled, what Shift to make to Recruit his Regiment, whereupon this Expedient was found out; there was in <hi>Gallway</hi> about 120 Prisoners, (who had been Seized for endeavouring to make an escape with Sir <hi>Thomas Southwell</hi> out of the <hi>Irish</hi> Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;) and who had endured the Miseries of Close Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Cold, Hunger, and a dayly expectation of a Violent Death for above 14 Months, Lying under Condemnation for Treason: To them Colonel <hi>Fielding</hi> applied himself, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to them, that for every one of them that would raise eight Men, and deliver them to him, to Recruit his Regiment, such should not only have their immediate Liberty, but an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Pardon for all that was past: and to that purpose he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced a Warrant for a General Pardon, which whether it were really the Act of the <hi>Late King,</hi> or only a Counterfeit Grant, and a Forgery, I cannot take upon me to Determin; But the poor Gentlemen overjoyed with the security of their Lives, and the prospect of their Liberty, consented readily to the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation; and with all earnestness betook themselves to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of what was expected on their parts, and in a very short time, about 14 of the Prisoners brought in the Number of Men demanded of them, and delivered them to the Conduct of the Colonel, who carried on the Intrigue without suspicion; but alas the poor unfortunate Gentlemen having Accomplisht their undertaking with extraordinary Pains and Charges, being obliged to pay great Sums of Mony to those Mercenary Men; no sooner was the Colonel with his Men Shipt away, but an Order was sent from the <hi>Late King,</hi> to Seize upon those deluded Gentlemen, and to recommit them to their former Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; on pretence that the Contract, made with them by Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:201495:12"/>
               <hi>Fielding,</hi> was not done with his Knowledg or Allowance. <hi>The great Turk</hi> would Blush to be charged with such an Action, and a very Heathen would abhor it, an Action only fit for the <hi>Mounsier of France,</hi> and such as are Influenced by his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>And now let me give you a Tast of the hopeful Fruits of an Arbitrary, unlimited and Dispensing Power, which the <hi>Late King claimed in</hi> Scotland, <hi>aim'd at in</hi> England, and hath been effectually <hi>exercized in</hi> Ireland: where (by his absolute <hi>Authority to be obeyed</hi> without reserve), he hath upon the great emergency of the occasion, caused a heavy Tax to be Levied of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by the naked Authority of a <hi>Proclamation,</hi> without the preliminary sanction of an Act of <hi>Parliament.</hi> And this that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows next is the very Tenor of it.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="proclamation">
                        <head>By the King a Proclamation.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <signed>James R.</signed>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WHereas we have received certain Information, that the Ʋsurper and his Adherents in <hi>England,</hi> are making great Preparations to make a fresh Invasion on this our Kingdom with a numerous Army, as well of <hi>Danes</hi> and other Foreigners, as of such of our own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects as they can seduce to take up Arms against us, and do threaten no less than the total Extirpation of all our Faithful Subjects of this Realm; We do therefore find our Self obliged to make use of the most effectual Means we can, for raising and maintaining a sufficient Force to oppose and repel so unnatural and so impious an Attempt: And whereas the Experience of all Times hath shewed, That an Army cannot be serviceable without good Order
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:201495:13"/> and Discipline, which may not be kept without making regular and due Payments, the only means to keep them from oppressing and plundering the People: And whereas the late Act of Supply has charged the Subsidy thereby granted towards the support of our Army, altogether on Lands and Tenements, and such Leases only as are set at half value, or under; which Subsidy, as it cannot be levied in some Parts of the Kingdom, now infested with the Rebels, nor out of some Lands which are waste; so it is not in it self sufficient to defray the Charges of the War; and since the Ʋrgency is so great upon this present Occasion, where no less than the Safety of the Publick, as well as of every Man in particular is concerned, as that it cannot admit of any delay; and therefore the ordinary Method of giving Supplies in Parliament, (always pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised in Setled Times) cannot be at present made use of without the loss of too much time; And since it cannot but seem reasonable, that where all Estates and all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees are equally at stake, the Personal Estates should contribute to the Common Defence: Wherefore after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Deliberation had with our Privy Council upon the present Affairs, and upon due Examination of what hath been done in the like extraordinary Exigencies in former times, We have thought fit by the Advice of our said Privy Council to order and declare, and we do hereby order and declare, That a Contribution of <hi>20000 l. per</hi> Month for the space of Three Months, ending the last day of <hi>January</hi> last past, shall be forthwith Applotted, Laid in, and Levied upon the Personal Estates of all sorts within this Kingdom (Houshold Goods, Apparel, and such Leases as are already Charged by the said Act of Supply, only excepted) and also upon the benefit of Trade, or Traffick;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:201495:13"/> and that all and every the Counties, Cities, and Corporations within this Kingdom, shall bear and pay so much, and in such and the like share and proportion of the Contribution, as they and every of them respectively do bear and pay of the aforesaid Subsidy already granted by the said Act of Supply; which said Contribution is to be equally Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotted by Commissioners, to be forthwith Named by us in each County, City, and Town Corporate, who shall make Books thereof, and proceed therein according to Instructions, which we shall forthwith cause to be published in that behalf, to the end that the same may be levied and paid with all speed, without which it cannot answer those good and necessary Ends for which it is intended. And for the better Enabling of all our Loving Subjects to pay this Contribution, and for securing them for the future against all free Quarterings, and other Oppressions and Injuries that may be offered them by any of our Army, We have further thought fit by the Advice aforesaid to declare, That we will forthwith appoint one or more Persons in each County and City within this Kingdom, who shall have power to receive all Complaints concerning any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions or Extortions, to be committed by any Officers or Souldiers of our Army, and out of our Revenue to make present Payment to the Parties aggrieved for the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by them sustained, and to return such Complaints to our Secretary of War, in order to have the value of such Damage deducted for us out of the Pay of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties offending and also to have them proceeded against ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Articles of War, which have been heretofore, or hereafter shall be by us made in that behalf.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given at our Court at <hi>Dublin Castle,</hi>
                              <date>the 4th day of <hi>February,</hi> 1689.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:201495:14"/>
            <p>As for <hi>Ship-Mony,</hi> and other heavy Burdens laid on the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in the Reign of King <hi>CHARLES the First,</hi> there was some colour of Law, and many Precedents produced to favour, if not to Warrant such Imposition; yet that was condemned by publick Acts of Parliament, and Judgments in the Kings Courts in <hi>Westminster.</hi> But at this time of Day, after all those Proceedings, for a King and his Privy Council, to impose and levy a Tax of <hi>Twenty Thousand Pounds per Mensem</hi> upon the Personal Estates, and the benefit of Trade, is a Strain of Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power, never before put in practice, except by <hi>Richard the Second;</hi> and what calamitous Effects that produced, and how Fatal to himself, the Histories of that Time do sufficiently testifie.</p>
            <p>Such Proceedings as these, tho' never so Arbitrary and Illegal, may yet receive some extenuation and excuse from the pressing Streights and irresistible exigency of Affairs; but for a King eagerly, wilfully, and considerately to break his Word, and violate his Solemn Promises, made, and often reiterated to his People, (as he called them) for the entire Maintenance and exact observance of the <hi>Act of Settlement in Ireland,</hi> is so dishonourable an Instance of Injustice, as is not to be reconciled with the ordinary methods of Morality: And if the Reader will give himself the trouble to look over the Act, lately made in <hi>The Mock Parliament</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (Entituled, <hi>An Act for the Repealing the Acts of Settlement and Explanation, &amp;c.</hi>) which he may find in the Book lately set forth, giving a <hi>List of the Persons lately Attainted in the Parliament there,</hi> pag. 51. which would be too tedious to recite here at large; he will be convinced, how little or no encouragement there is for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> to expect any security under a <hi>Popish King,</hi> who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not only at his pleasure dispense with the established Laws of the Land, but can procure a Dispensation from a Power (to which he has blindly made himself subordinate) for the Iniquity of such irregular Actions.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:201495:14"/>
            <p>And since we see that he came by the Power of a <hi>French</hi> Army, to Reassume what he had Abdicated, only to subject us to the Tyranny of <hi>France</hi> and their Dragoons; what Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have we <hi>Hereticks</hi> (as they call us,) (with whom no person of his Perswasion is to keep Faith) to hope, much less to believe, that he will keep or perform any Promise for the benefit of a <hi>Protestant,</hi> having in so many almost innumerable Instances, before his Deserting the People of <hi>England,</hi> Violated every Individual part of that Solemn Oath taken at his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <p>But as if all that hath been before observed, were slight and trivial Matters, and not of force sufficient to undeceive the grumbling Generation of Men, let every wavering and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satisfied Person, duly and without Prejudice weigh and consider the <hi>Act of Attainder,</hi> lately past in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein he shall observe, not only the utmost Severity, Partiality, and Injustice done to the <hi>Protestants,</hi> but manag'd in so fallacious a manner, that the whole Proceeding is complicated with Fraud, Trep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anning and Circumvention. For the secret Machinations of the <hi>Papists,</hi> and the open and uncontroll'd Outrages done by them on the Persons, Estates, and Goods of the <hi>Protestants,</hi> are too notorious, and may justly excuse them before God and Man, and warrant their voluntary withdrawing themselves from under the Tyranny of their implacable Enemies and Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors; yet the Process against them hath been managed with so much Art, Fallacy, and Surprize, that it is morally impossible for any <hi>Protestant</hi> to avoid the Forfeiture of Life and Estate. Indeed no other Quarter or Usage could rationally be expected from a Parliament, wherein its to be noted, that Nine parts of Ten were the <hi>Macs, O's,</hi> and <hi>Clans:</hi> In a word, The Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of those Vulturs, who for their Rebellion and horrid Treason in 1641, justly forfeited all they could pretend to; and at the Sitting of this Parliament were not worth one Groat, but what they had since <hi>August</hi> 1688, plunder'd and taken from the <hi>Protestants.</hi> For conceiving that the Kingdom was their own, and that they had received the accomplishment of their Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations and Attempts for several Ages past, <hi>The total extirpation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:201495:15"/> of the British Names and Blood;</hi> they began to exert all the Articles which inveterate Malice, (whetted with an inreconcilable Aversion to the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi>) could suggest And First, for such as either had not a convenient opportunity to escape, or were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely determin'd to abide the Brunt, and continue under their Protection, they found this Expedient to promote, and ascertain their Destruction; They Issued out Warrants to the Sheriffs of the respective Counties, where the <hi>Estates of the Protestants</hi> lay, while their Persons were under their Power, and in their sight in <hi>Dublin;</hi> and so proceeding by way of secret Outlawries, they brought them under the Attainder, confiscated their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Estates, and Seized the Real, delivering over the Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to the old Proprietors, or whom else they pleased. It were easie to demonstrate this in the case of several Persons, as—</p>
            <p>And as for those whom they term Absentees, they have dealt with them most disingenuously (to say no worse of it) and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them as Exiles, and proscribed Persons; for having collected a Schedule of their Names, they foisted them into a Proclamation, limiting their return to certain fixt days; some in <hi>September,</hi> some in <hi>October,</hi> some in <hi>November;</hi> but in the mean time they took especial Care, that no Noise should be made of it, and lest the sound of such a Warning-Piece should reach into <hi>England, Scotland</hi> or the <hi>Isle</hi> of <hi>Man;</hi> They provided so, that no such <hi>Proclamation</hi> should be made publick, till the several days of Grace were Elapsed; And then by virtue of the <hi>Act against Absentees,</hi> they presently Seized on all the Personal Estates of such Persons, and confiscated them to the use of the late King. I shall trouble the Reader only with the Preamble, and a few of the first Lines in it, being <hi>Entituled, An Act for Forfeiting and Vesting in his Majesty the Goods of Absentees.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:201495:15"/>
            <head>Here follows the <hi>Act of Attainder,</hi> Past in the Parliament Assembled in <hi>Dublin</hi> by the Late King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>May 1689;</hi> by which Act, and the most disingenuous Proceedings of that <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>Late King,</hi> Destruction is thunder'd against Thousands of all Degrees and Qualities of Men, Women and Infants.</head>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="act">
                        <head>An Act for Forfeiting, and Vesting in his <hi>Majesty,</hi> the Goods of Absen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHereas</hi> upon the General Defection of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Subjects in <hi>England,</hi> several of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Subjects have Deserted this Kingdom, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired into your Majesties Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and elsewhere; thereby Endeavouring to weaken your Majesties Interest here, and shewing an Apparent diffidence of your Majesties Protection; most of which Persons have Actually taken Arms, under the unnatural Usurper in <hi>England;</hi> and divers others of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Subjects became Rebels and Traytors within this your Realm: And forasmuch, as the said Persons have left behind them several Goods and Chattels, and personal Estates, part whereof hath been Seized in your Majesties Name, or otherwise by several Persons, who have not yet answered, or accounted for the same to your Majesty.</p>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:201495:16"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Be it therefore Enacted</hi> by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, with the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by the Authority of the same, that all Goods and Chattels, Corn in Ground, Debts by Judgments, Statutes, Bonds, Bills, Books or otherwise; and all Arrears of Rent, belonging to any Person or Persons, in Rebellion against your Majesty, out of this your Majesties Kingdom; or belonging to any Person or Persons, that by any Act of this present Parliament, shall be Adjudged and Declared a forfeiting Person, or Persons Absent, and all other Persons Absent out of this Realm, and that Aid, Abet or Assist the said <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> Minors under the Age of Seventeen years; and such Person or Persons, who are Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to such Goods or Chattels, or Debts, as aforesaid in trust for others, who are not Absent, or Joyned with the Rebels; and such Person or Persons, as for some Reasonable cause to be allowed of, and approved under the Hands of the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of your Majesties Revenue in this Kingdom, or the major part of them; within three Months after the Royal Assent gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to this Act, always Excepted and Foreprized, shall from the Fifth day of <hi>November</hi> last, be, and hereby are vested in, and setled in your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors, and that all Person and Persons, who since the said Fifth day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> last, have Seized or possessed themselves of any Goods or Chattels belonging, or pretended to belong to any Person or Persons, upon pretence of such Person or Persons being in Rebellion, or Absent out of this your Majesties Realm: And all Persons, who since the First day of <hi>May</hi> last, have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved any Arrears of Rent or Debts, due to any Person or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, who are or have been in Rebellion, or now are Absent out of your Majesties Kingdom, <hi>Be and are hereby</hi> Declared to be Debtors and Accountants to your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors; and such Person and Persons, shall by Process out of your Majesties Court of Exchequer, to be (Issued within two Years and no longer,) be made chargeable and liable as in other Debts, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>[<hi>This last part is for their own benefit, otherwise they might
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:201495:16"/> have spared the trouble they took in framing the Act; for in</hi> March, April <hi>and</hi> May, <hi>before their Parliament Sate, Persons appointed, and same without any Authority came to Absentees, nay, to some wherein the Protestants remain'd, and under the Pretence of Absentees Goods, or Searching for Arms, they carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way what Goods they pleased; and the Commissioners sent for the Agents and Servants of the Absentees, administring what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories they pleased; and if the Servants refused or could not discover any thing, they were Committed;</hi> As for Instance, One Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> who (tho he was a Roman Catholick, yet) out of a Spark of Gratitude, and a Principle of Honesty, and Integrity to his Trust; would not discover his Master the Duke of <hi>Ormonds</hi> Writings and Rentals, or deliver them, whereupon he was confined for a considerable time. [See in the Margin of the Book, wherein this Act of Parliament is much to the same effect, Fol. 41]</p>
            <p>In the next place, I shall Recite the Clauses in the <hi>Act of Attainder,</hi> relating to the Absentees, and then offer some plain obvious Remarks upon them.</p>
            <p>And First, The Scene opens Tragically, and Thunders Destruction to some Hundreds of Lords, Baronets and Knights, together with some Thousands of Gentlemen, and others in these words; <hi>Be in Enacted</hi> by your most Excellent Majesty, by and with the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by Authority of the same, That the Persons hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Named, being Persons who <hi>have Notoriously joyned in the said Rebellion and Invasion;</hi> and some of which are upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment Condemned, some Executed for High Treason, and the rest Run away or Abscond, or are now in the Actual Service of the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> against your Majesty, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers killed in open Rebellion, viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis March</hi> Lord Archbishop of <hi>Dublin, James Butler</hi> Duke of <hi>Ormond, Richard Boyl</hi> Earl of <hi>Cork;</hi> and then after enumerating some Thousands of Names, (the Act goes on and says:) whether Dead or Alive, or Killed in open Rebellion, or now in Arms against your Majesty, or otherwise; and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:201495:17"/> every of them shall be deem'd, taken, reputed, and are hereby De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and Adjudged Traytors, Convicted and Attainted of High Treason; and shall suffer such pains of Death, Penalties and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, respectively, as in Cases of High Treason are accustom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>Provided</hi> that in case it happen, that any of the Persons hereby Attainted, or to be Attainted, do now abide or dwell in this Kingdom, and are ameanable to the Law, that then and in such case, if such Person and Persons, do by the Tenth day of <hi>August,</hi> 1689. without compulsion, of his own accord, come in and deliver himself▪ to the Lord Chief Justice of his Majesties Court of Kings Bench in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or to any other of the Judges of the said Court, or any other of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties four Courts in <hi>Dublin;</hi> or to any Judge of Assize in their Circuits, to be charged with any Treason, to be Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him or them, That then and in such Case such Person and Persons, if after acquitted by the Law of this Land, or discharged by Proclamation, shall be freed, discharged and accquitted from all pains punishments and forfeitures by this <hi>Act</hi> incurred, laid or imposed. Any thing in this Act to the Contrary in any wise notwithstanding in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A multitude of names are Mustered up as Absen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, and their Doom runs thus,</p>
            <p>And whereas the several Persons hereafter named, viz. <hi>John Veasy</hi> Lord Archbishop of <hi>Tuam, Arthur Chichester</hi> Earl of <hi>Donnegall, Falliot Wingfield</hi> Viscount <hi>Powerscourt, William Morton</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Killdare,</hi> with some Hundreds more, as in the former Printed Book of the Names, from page 24 to page 30, (and says) have Absconded themselves from this Kingdom, and have gon into <hi>England,</hi> or some other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beyond the Seas since the Fifth day of <hi>November</hi> last, or in some short time before, and did not return, although called home by Their Majesties Gracious Proclamation; which absconding, and not returning, cannot be construed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than a wicked and Traiterous purpose, and may thereby justly forfeit all their Right and Pretensions to all and every the Lands▪ Tenements and Hereditaments to them belonging in this Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:201495:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it therefore Enacted</hi> by the Authority aforesaid, That in case the said person and persons do not by the first Day of <hi>September,</hi> 1689. of his or their own accord, without compulsion, return into this Kingdom, and tender him and themselves to the Chief Justice of his Majesty's Court of Kings Bench, or to some other Judge of the said Court, or Judge of Assizes in the Circuit, or any of the Lords of your Majesties most Honourable Privy Council, to be charged with any Crimes to him or them to be imputed, (that then) or in case he or they, upon his or their Return, shall be Convict by Verdict of Twelve Men, or by his or their own Confession, upon his or their Arraignment for Treason, or upon his or their Arraignment stand Mute; such person and persons so absent, and not returning as aforesaid, or after his or their Return, being Convict of Treason, as aforesaid, shall from and after the said First day of <hi>September,</hi> 1689, be deemed, reputed and taken as Traytors convict and attainted of High Treason, and shall suffer such pains of Death, and other Forfeitures and Penalties, as in cases of High Treason are accustomed: But in case such person and persons so Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, be upon such his or their Tryal <hi>Acquitted</hi> or <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged</hi> by Proclamation, then such person and persons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectively, shall from thenceforth be freed, discharged, and acquitted from all Pains, Punishments, and Forfeitures, by this Act incurred, laid, or imposed; Any thing in this Act to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>[<hi>This Sentence being past against the Absentees,</hi>]</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A multitude of Names [as in the former printed List of Names, pag. 31.] are muster'd up as Absentees, and their Doom runs thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas</hi> the several persons hereafter named, <hi>viz. Robert▪ Ridgway</hi> Earl of <hi>Londonderry, Arthur Loftis</hi> Viscount <hi>Loftis</hi> of <hi>Eli,</hi> with about 500 more, before the Fifth Day of <hi>November</hi> last, absented themselves from this Kingdom, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:201495:18"/> live in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> or the Isle of <hi>Man,</hi> and there now abide, and by not coming or returning into this Kingdom upon your Majesties Proclamation, to assist in Defence of this Realm according to their Allegiance, must be presumed to adhere to the said <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> in case they return not within the time in this Act prescribed, and thereby may justly forfeit all the Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Hereditaments, which they or any of them are entituled unto within this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it therefore Enacted</hi> by the Authority aforesaid, That in case the said person and persons last mentioned, do by the first day of <hi>October</hi> 1689. of his and their own accord, without compulsion, Return into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and tender him and themselves to the Chief Justice of your Majesties Court of Kings Bench, or to some other Judge of the said Court or Judge of Assize in his Circuit, or to any of the Lords of your Majesties most Honourable Privy Council, <hi>To be charged with any Crime or Crimes,</hi> to him or them to be charged or imputed, that then, in case that he or they upon such his or their Return shall be convict by Verdict of Twelve Men, or by his own Confession upon his or their Arraignment for Treason, or upon his or their Arraignment stand Mute; such person and persons <hi>so Absent, and not Returning as aforesaid, or after his or their Return, being convict of Treason, as aforesaid, shall from and after the said First day of</hi> October 1689. <hi>be deemed, reputed, and taken as Traytors Convict, and Attainted of High Treason, and shall suffer such Pains of Death, and other Forfeitures and Penalties, as in Cases of High Treason is accustomed:</hi> But in case such person and persons respectively shall return, they shall from thenceforth be freed, discharged and acquitted from all Pains, Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Forfeitures by this Act incurr'd, laid, or imposed; any thing in this Act to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
            <p>Which terrible Clause in the Act seems to be sweetned
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:201495:18"/> by a most gracious Proviso extended to a select number of Persons which goes on in these Words: Provided always, That in case your Majesty shall happen to go into the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> before the said first day of <hi>October</hi> 1689. Then if the said Sir <hi>William Meredith,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Chiney,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Loyd,</hi> Sir <hi>Algernoon Mayo,</hi> Sir <hi>Joseph Williamson,</hi> Sir <hi>William Parker, Alexander Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier</hi> Esq; <hi>John Hollum, Daniel</hi> of the Iron-works, <hi>Brook Bridges, Charles Vaughan, Hugh Merick, Nathaniel Huet, Heirom Hawkins,</hi> Major <hi>John Read, William Trenchard, J—Trenchard</hi> his Eldest Son, <hi>Erasmus Smith, Harison</hi> of <hi>Balvarneen, Achilles Daniel, John Lovet, John Castle, Joseph Rutterton, Thomas Valentine</hi> Clark of <hi>Ballyturmey, John Cright, George Clarke</hi> of <hi>Shaccrelin, Thomas Chinucks, William Warmsby, Richard Cluterbuck, Erasmus Smith, William Wats, John Evelin, Thapcote</hi> of <hi>Loughkent, Page</hi> of the same▪ <hi>Thomas Moor, Humphry Wray, Edward Crafton,</hi> Alderman <hi>Clarke, John Clarke, Arthur Aneste, William Warwick, Purefy Warwick▪</hi> Captain <hi>Coaps, Robert Boye</hi> of <hi>Kilgrant, Hugh Ratclif, Edward Nelthrop, Robert Dixon, Samuel Clarke, John Jones, Henry Payne, George Clark</hi> and <hi>Gilbert Thacker,</hi> whose Dwellings and Residence always hath been in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See in the former printed List of the Names,</hi> pag. 30 &amp; 31. <hi>has more names than ought to be in that Clause and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not true.</hi>
               </note> shall give your Majesty such Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Loyalty, and Fidelity as that your Majesty will be pleased on or before the said first day of <hi>October,</hi> 1689. to certifie under your Privy Signet or Sign Manual unto the chief Governor or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of this Kingdom, that your Majesty is satisfied and assured of the Loyalty and Fidelity of the Persons last before named, or of any of them; that then, if such Certificate shall on or before the First day of <hi>November</hi> 1689, be produced to the chief Governor or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of this Kingdom, and Enrolled▪ in your Majesties High Court of Chancery, the same shall be a sufficient Discharge and Acquittal to such of the Persons last be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:201495:19"/> named, and every of them respectively, whose Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Fidelity your Majesty will be pleased to certify in manner as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And be it further Enacted,</hi> That in the mean time, and until such Return and Acquittal, all the Lands Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Hereditaments within this Kingdom belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all and every Absentee and Absentees, or other Person to be attainted as aforesaid, shall be, and are hereby vested in your Majesty, your Heirs and Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, as from the first day of <hi>August</hi> last past.</p>
            <p>Then comes the Stabbing Clause, with a Face like <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> Looking forward and backward both at once, in this tenor. <hi>And be it further Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said,</hi> that all and every such Person and Persons, as by any the foregoing Clauses is, are or shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectively attainted, shall be from the first day of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust,</hi> One Thousand, Six Hundred Eighty and Eight, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit unto your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors, <hi>all such Mannors, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, all Right, Title, Service, Chiefry, Ʋse, Trust, Condition, Fee, Rent Charge, Right of Redemption of Mortgages, Right of Entries, Right of action, or any other Interest of what nature or Kind soever, either</hi> in Law or Equity, of, in or into any Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, within this Kingdom, belonging or appertaining to such Person or Persons, so as aforesaid attainted, or to be attainted in his or their own Right, or to any other Interest for him or them on the said first day of <hi>August,</hi> 1689, or at any time since; and all the said Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, so as aforesaid forfeited unto, and vested in your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, are and shall be vested in your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors, whether such Person or Persons were sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed thereof in Fee Absolute or Conditional, or in Tail, or for Life or Lives, and that freed and freely dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, of and from <hi>all Estates Tail, and for Life;</hi> and from all Reversions and Remainders for Life, for Years,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:201495:19"/> or in Fee Absolute or Conditional, or in Tail for any Person or Persons whatsoever, such Remainders, as by one Act or Statute of this present Parliament, Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, An Act for Repealing the Act of Settlement and Explanation, Resolution of the Doubts, and all Grants, Patents and Certificates pursuant to them, or any of them, or by this present Act, are saved and preserved, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways excepted and foreprized: <hi>Provided always,</hi> that any Remissness or Forfeiture of any Tenant in Dower, Tenant by the Curtesie, Jointress for Life, or other Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for Life or Lives in actual Possession, shall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to bar, forfeit, make void or discharge any Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion vested in any Person or Persons not ingaged in the Usurpation or Rebellion aforesaid, such Reversion and Reversions being immediately depending or expectant upon the particular Estate of such Tenant in Dower, Tenant by the Courtesie, Joyntress for Life, or other Tenant for Life or Lives, any thing in the said Act of <hi>Repeal,</hi> or in this present Act to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. <hi>Provided always, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,</hi> that nothing in this present Act contained, shall any way extend to be construed, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to forfeit or vest in your Majesty, your Heirs or Successors any Remainder or Remainders for valuable consideration limited or setled by any settlement or conveyance made for such valuable consideration, either of Marriage or Marriage Portion, or other valuable consideration whatsoever, upon any Estate for Life or Lives, to any Person or Persons not concerned in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surpation or Rebellion aforesaid, such Remainder or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders, as are limited or setled by any conveyance wherein there is any power for revoking and altering all or any the use or uses therein limited; and also such Remainder and Remainders as are limited upon any Settlement or Conveyance of any Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Hereditaments commonly called Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Lands; and all Lands, Tenements and Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:201495:20"/> held or enjoyed under such Grants from the Crown, or Grants upon the Commission, or Commissions of Grace, for remedy of defective Titles, either in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the First, or King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, in which several Grants respectively, there are Provisoes or Covenants for raising or keeping any number of Men or Arms for the King's Majesty against Rebels or Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or for raising of Men for his Majesties Service, for expedition of War, always excepted, and foreprised, all which Remainders limited by such conveyances wherein there is a power of Revocation for so much of the Lands, Uses and Estates therein limited, as the said power doth or shall Extend unto; and all such Remainders as are derived or limited, from or under such Interest made of such Plantation Lands, or other Lands held as aforesaid, under such Grants from the Crown, and all and every other Remainder and Remainders, Reversion and Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, not herein mentioned to be saved and preserved, shall by Authority of this present Parliament be deemed, construed and adjudged void, debarred and discharged to all intents and purposes whatsoever against your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, your Heirs and Successors, and yours and their Grantees or Assigns, and the said Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments belonging to such Rebels as aforesaid, shall be vested in your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors freed and discharged from the said Remainder and Remainders saved and preserved by this Act, and that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with all convenient speed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,</hi> That the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Persons Intituled to such Remainders and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions, do within Sixty days next after the first sitting of the Commissioners for Examining the said Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, and this present Act, exhibit their Claims before the said Commissioners, and make out their Titles to such Remainder or Remainders, so as to procure their Adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, and Certificate for the same, or the Adjudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Certificate of some Three or more of them; and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:201495:20"/> further, that all Remainders for which such Adjudication and Certificate shall not be procured at or before One Hundred and Twenty days after the first sitting of the said Commissioners, shall be void, and for ever Barred or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; any thing in this Act, or other matter to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in any wise notwithstanding. All which Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, and Hereditaments, mentioned as aforesaid, to be forfeited unto, and vested in your Majesty by any the Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses aforesaid, and are hereby declared to be so forfeited unto, and vested in your Majesty, without any▪ Office or Inquisition thereof found or to be found, and the same to be to the Uses, Intents and Purposes, as in the said Act of Repeal, and in this present Act mentioned and expressed.</p>
            <p>The Fifth is a wheedling Clause to amuse a certain small number of Women, Widows, Minors and Sick-Persons with a seeming Latitude to return: but their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states are sure to be vested in the King till they do, as more at large you may see, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas the several Persons hereafter named, <hi>viz. Lyonel</hi> Earl of <hi>Orrery▪</hi> Mrs. <hi>Traps, Anne</hi> Vicountess Dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Dungannon, Robert Boyl</hi> Esquire, <hi>Katherine Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock, Alice</hi> Countess Dowager of <hi>Drogheda,</hi> and the rest, as in the former Book of the Persons attainted. <hi>p.</hi> 37, 38, to about the number of Eighty Persons, are and for some time past, have been absent out of this Kingdom, and by reason of Sickness, Nonage, Infirmities, and other disabilities, may for some time further be obliged so to stay out of this Kingdom, or be disabled to return thereunto. Nevertheless, it being much to the weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Realm, that any of the Rents or Profits of the Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments therein, should be sent into or spent in any other Place beyond the Seas, but that the same should be Kept and Employed within the Realm for the better support and defence thereof; <hi>Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said,</hi> that all the Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:201495:21"/> Use, Trust, Possession, Reversion, Remainder, and all and every other Estate, Title and Interest whatsoever belonging or appertaining to all and every the Persons herein before last mentioned within this Kingdom, be and are hereby vested in your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors. <hi>Provided always,</hi> that if any Person or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in the next foregoing Clause mentioned, have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto behaved themselves Loyally and Faithfully to your Majesty, that then, if they or any of them, their or any of their Heirs do hereafter return into this Kingdom, and behave him, or themselves as becometh Loyal Subjects, and do on or before the Last day of the first Term next ensuing, after such their return, Exhibit his or their Petition or Claim, before the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for Executing the said Acts, (if then sitting,) or in his Majesties high Court of Chancery, or in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Court of Exchequer for any such Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Hereditaments, and make out his or their Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thereunto, and obtain the Adjudication and Decree of any of the said Courts of and for such his or their Title, that then and in such case, such Adjudication and Decree shall be sufficient to all such Person and Persons, for devesting and restoring such Estate, and no other as shall be therein and thereby to him or them adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and decreed; and that the order of any of the said Courts shall be sufficient Warrant to all Sheriffs, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proper Officer to whom the same shall be directed, to put such Person or Persons in the actual Seizing and Possession of the said Land, any thing in this Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, or any other Statute, Law or Custom whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided always, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,</hi> that neither the said Act of Repeal, or this present Act, or any thing in them or either of them contained shall extend to, or be construed to forfeit or vest in your Majesty, your Heirs or Successors, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to Barr, Extinguish or Weaken, any right of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:201495:21"/> right of Action, Use, Trust, Lease, Condition or Equity of Redemption, of any Mortgage or Mortgages, which on the first day of <hi>August,</hi> 1688, belonged or appertained to any Person or Persons not being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting Persons within the true Intent and Meaning of the said Act of Repeal, or this present Act, and which ever since the first day of <hi>August,</hi> 1688, continued or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in such Persons, not being Persons, or descend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or devolved, or come from them, or any of them, to any of their Heirs, Executors or Administrators, not being forfeiting Persons as aforesaid, any thing in this or the said Act of Repeal to the contrary notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Provided always,</hi> that the Person or Persons claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such right of Entry, right of Action, Use, Trust, Lease, Condition or Equity of Redemption, of Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, do and shall Exhibit his and their claim for the same, before the Commissioners for Execution of the said Act of Repeal, or of this present Act within Sixty days after the first sitting of the said Commissioners, and procure the Adjudication of them, or any three or more of them thereupon, within one Hundred and Twenty days after the said first sitting of the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas,</hi> by one or more Office or Offices in the time of the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi>'s Government, in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the First of ever Blessed Memory, all or a great part of the Lands, Tenements, and Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Province of <hi>Connaught,</hi> and Counties of <hi>Clare, Limerick</hi> and <hi>Tiperary,</hi> were vested in his Majesty, and by the Acts of Settlement or Explanation, the said Office and Offices are declared to be null and void; since which time, the said Acts have been by the said Acts of Repeal Repealed, and thereby some prejudice might arise or accrew to the Proprietors concerned in them Lands, if not prevented. <hi>Be it therefore Enacted,</hi> by the Authority aforesaid, that the said Office and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and every of them, commonly called the Grand
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:201495:22"/> Office, and the Title thereby found or endeavoured to be made out, or set up from the time of finding or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof, was and is hereby declared to be null and void to all intents and purposes whatsoever: Provided always that nothing herein contained, shall any way extend to charge any Person or Persons who hath <hi>bona fide</hi> paid any Rent, or Arrears of Rent, that has been due and payable out of any Lands hereby vested in your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty; or to charge any Steward or Receiver that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any such Rents or Arrears of Rent, if he <hi>bona fide</hi> paid the same; but that he and they shall be hereby discharged for so much as he or they so <hi>bona fide</hi> paid against your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided always, and it is hereby Enacted,</hi> that every Person not being a forefeiting Person, within the true intent and meaning of the said former Act, or of this present Act, and who before the Seventh day of <hi>May,</hi> 1689, had any Statute Staple, or Recognizance for payment of Money, or any Mortgage, Rent Charge, Portion, Trust, or other Incumbrance either in Law or Equity; or any Judgement before the Two and Twentieth day of <hi>May,</hi> 1689, for payment of Mony which might charge any of the Estates, Lands, Tenements and Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments so as aforesaid forfeited unto, and vested in your Majesty, shall and may have the benefit of the said Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes Staple Judgments, Recognizances, Mortgages, Rents Charges, Portions, Trusts, and other Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances out of the Estate or Estates, which would be liable thereunto, in case the said former Act or this present Act had never been made. <hi>Provided always,</hi> that the Person and Persons who had such Statutes Staple, Judgments, Recognizances or other Trusts or Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, do claim the same before the Commissioners, for Execution of the said former Act within two Months after the first sitting of the said Commissioners, and procure their Adjudication thereof, within such reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time as the said Commissioners shall appoint for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:201495:22"/> the same. And to the end that such Person and Persons as shall have any of the said Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Hereditaments so to be granted unto him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Incumbrances, and may injoy the same against all Statutes Staple, Judgments, Recognizances, Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages, Rents Charge, and other Incumbrances, not claimed and adjudged as aforesaid. <hi>Be it therefore further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,</hi> that all such Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments as shall be forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto, and vested in your Majesty, and granted by Letters Patents pursuant to the said former Act, or this present, shall be, and are hereby freed and acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and discharged of and from all Estates, Charges and Incumbrances whatsoever, other than what shall be claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and adjudged as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Upon the First I do observe, that after they are all marked with a black Coal, and actually <hi>attainted of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son whether Dead or Alive, Killed in open Rebellion, or in Arms, or otherwise;</hi> (i. e.) wheresoever they are, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever they are doing, there is a very merciful saving extended to them under these favourable conditions: First, They must be commorant and resident <hi>in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> Secondly, That they must be ameanable to Law. Thirdly, That they must by the Tenth day of <hi>August,</hi> 1689, surrender themselves to Justice. Fourthly, That they shall be discharged by Proclamation, if they shall be acquitted upon their Tryal; while all this is nothing but palpable Collusion and Banter, they very well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that such as had taken Arms, were either out of the Kingdom, or resident in the <hi>Protestant</hi> Quarters, that it was impossible, for them, or the greatest part of them, to make their appearance by the tenth of <hi>August</hi> 1689. That no Man who had not forfeited Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and common Sense, would come in with a Halter about his Neck, and try whether they could find a Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; or being subject to the pains of High-treason, to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:201495:23"/> make an experiment of the Justice of <hi>Popish Judges,</hi> and the Mercy of a <hi>Popish Jury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the second Clause relating to the <hi>Abscondees,</hi> A time is aflowed them to the first <hi>of September</hi> 1689. to return and appear: But upon what Conditions? (why) only that they shall <hi>of their own accord render themselves to Justice,</hi> and then, <hi>if by the Verdict of</hi> twelve Men <hi>they shall he Convicted</hi> of Treason (which beyond all doubt or question would be the Fate of every one of them,) they are to be decently, and legally <hi>Beheaded</hi> or <hi>Hang'd:</hi> and if any of them shall upon his Tryal be acquitted or discharged, then to be freed from all Penalties and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, which indeed, in good reason ought so to be, but so much Indifferency and Candor is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from <hi>Cannibals.</hi> And for my part I would as soon believe <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> or trust to be saved by the Supererogation of other Mens Merits.</p>
            <p>The third, which seems to have an aspect only on such as are denominated Absentees, is as full fraught with Tricks and Designs, as it abounds with Mischief and Malice; for to say nothing of that great number of Gentlemen, Merchants and Tradesmen, who for the necessary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of their Lives, have been constrain'd to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fent themselves, and seek a Shelter in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and the <hi>Isle of Man;</hi> there are many of the Nobility and Gentry of and in <hi>England,</hi> who are exposed to the reach of this fatal Summons, who never were commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in <hi>Ireland,</hi> never saw the Country, and possibly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended to see it, yet they are obliged under pain of High Treason, and Forfeiture of Lives and Estates, to appear there by the first of <hi>October</hi> 1689. and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themselves to some Magistrate, and submit to a Tryal for such <hi>Crimes</hi> as it pleases their Enemies to sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest, and their Prosecutors to urge. Many others of them have been absent, and setled in <hi>England</hi> for divers Years, some for above twenty; yet it is expected that they must now take upon them a Winter Journy, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:201495:23"/> patiently submit to be hang'd for presuming to cross the Seas, when there might be after an unforeseen oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to employ <hi>their Service;</hi> but it hath so fallen out, that neither the one nor the other hath been terrified by these Threats which they never heard of till long after the day of Grace was expired, but have rather adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to run the Risque, and be devested of their Estates for a while, no way doubting of a Recovery and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution in good time. Against this terrible Storm there is but one Anchor to trust to; and that to be rely'd on only by a select number, and that is to give <hi>such Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Loyalty and Fidelity to</hi> King James, <hi>in case he shall happen</hi> to go into <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> before the first day of <hi>October</hi> 1689. as that upon a Certificate from him, and the Inrolment of it in Chancery <hi>before the first day of</hi> November 1689. they may be white Boys again: But forasmuch as the late King hath not thought it fit to come upon the Place, and make his demand, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them absolved from all breach of Duty, tho at the same time they have slipt all other Opportunites of purchasing their Pardon.</p>
            <p>The fourth enacting Clause is so Comprehensive, so armed at all Points against all manner of Excuses, Subterfuges and Evasions, that whosoever shall flatter himself with a hope of Security in that Harbour, will certainly split upon a Rock; He that shall wade in that Tempestuous Sea, shall never be able to stem the Tide: For in a Word, All sorts of Estates, Rights and Properties belonging to all sorts of Men, except the Rebellious and Bloody Irish, and such unhappy Persons as have been bewitched into a Confederacy with them, are doom'd to an irreversible Forfeiture, and vested <hi>in the late King,</hi> and that Title thereunto, to commence <hi>from the first of August</hi> 1688. when all Things were quiet, <hi>in alta Pace,</hi> and many Months were past after that day, before there was the least umbrage given of any Opposition, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but then to clap in an useless Proviso, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:201495:24"/> all Persons <hi>claiming any Reversions</hi> or <hi>Remainders,</hi> are stinted to exhibite them within sixty days after the first sitting of their new fangled Commissioners, and to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure an Adjudication or Certificate</hi> from them within one hundred and twenty <hi>days after the first sitting,</hi> is a Rule so Repugnant to Reason, Law and Equity, that it evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears to be contrived on purpose to jeer and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule the poor Sufferers; For could it be imagined that any <hi>Protestants</hi> would adventure to go among them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Flames of a raging War, to make a demand of a present or future Title, and stay there if they might be suffered, till that very precious Court for Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judication of Claims should fit, and be established? <hi>but the burden of the Song is; let all be vested in his Majesty.</hi> And thus, whether they be attainted as <hi>Absentees,</hi> or found guilty upon the Tryal, or rejected in their Claims before the Commissioners, all is summoned up in one and the same Conclusion, the whole Estates of the <hi>Protestants</hi> Real and Personal, must be forfeited, and the <hi>King must</hi> have them towards a <hi>Reprisal</hi> of what he <hi>abdicated</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same Spirit and Humor runs in the fifth declarative and enacting Clause, pretending a Shadow of Favour to certain Persons therein named by reason of Minority, Widowhood, or Sickness, but canting in the same strain with the former Clause and Proviso's, so that all Sexes and Degrees, according to their Design and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, are irrecoverably barred from all Possession, Right, Remainder or Reversion, so long as they can be prosperous in this Holy War, which is apparently ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a National, as well as a Religious Quarrel.</p>
            <p>I am very unwilling to imploy the Reader with a nauseous Repetition of any Matter couched in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Observations, which cannot be avoided if I should go about to make a direct Answer to the Absurdities in each single Paragraph, of that famous Act of Attainder whereby the <hi>Irish</hi> have fully and apparently demonscrated
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:201495:24"/> to the world, that as <hi>English Men,</hi> they look upon us as Intruders; as <hi>Protestants,</hi> they treat us as Miscreants and Hereticks. And since neither the horrible Murder per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated in the last Rebellion, nor the present burning of Houses, destruction of Plantations, general depopula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Country, are like to be available to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish the Families, and subvert the Religion; They have now tryed their utmost effort, by Seizing and Confisca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all Personal Estates, and by the absolute alienation of all their Rights, Titles, and Interests, so that from henceforth it was intended that no <hi>English Protestant</hi> must dare to set his Foot in <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor his Children call to mind that ever any of his Forefathers had a footing there.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless upon the review of the remaining part of the <hi>Act of Attainder,</hi> it will not be amiss to offer a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version to the Reader, by making some brief Remarks on the injustice, subtilty and partiality comprehended in it. For Men after they are actually attainted, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to appear and shew cause why they should not be Executed; their Appearance is limited to certain days and times. And lest any inconsiderate Man should be so Fool-hardy, as to adventure on his Purgation, there is no publick notice given of the Appearance required, till the days are Incurred and past; they are obliged to put in Claims, and to solicite an Adjudication before certain <hi>partial and prejudicated Commissioners,</hi> who are to meet, none knows when; and will determine none knows what: Nay, in some cases, they are positively appointed to put in their claim within Two Months after the first sitting of such Commissioners, and afterwards <hi>to procure their Adjudication within such Reasonable time, as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners shall appoint for determining the same.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And because a private Act past in the Reign of King <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> in favour of the Renowned <hi>Duke of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemarle,</hi> whereby several <hi>Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, are conveyed to him,</hi> in testimony of the greatest and most
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:201495:25"/> important service that ever was performed by a Subject, yet because <hi>the ancient Proprietors of the said Lands,</hi> (i. e.) those notorious Rebels, and Murderers, who justly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited for their Treason, are thereby barred and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of their ancient Estates, that Act must be repealed, and the ancient Proprietors restored; which is a high piece of Ingratitude to the memory of that Illustrious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, who under God, effected the Restoration of the Royal Family, and even of their very King <hi>James</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; the Reader may be pleased to peruse the Clause it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and Judge of the reasonableness and Civility of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas</hi> by one private Act of Parliament, Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>An Act for securing of several Lands, Tenements and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments to</hi> George <hi>Duke of</hi> Albemarle, which Act was past in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, some Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Hereditaments on this Kingdom, which on the Two and Twentieth day of <hi>October,</hi> 1641, belonged to some ancient Proprietor or Proprietors, who were dispossessed thereof by the late Usurped Powers, were secured or assured unto the said <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marle,</hi> by means whereof, the ancient Proprietors of the said Lands may be barred and deprived of their ancicnt Estates, unless the said Act be Repealed; though such ancient Proprietor or Proprietors, be as justly Intituled to Restitution, as other ancient Proprietors, who were dispossessed by the said Usurper, and barred by the late Acts of Settlement and Explanation. <hi>Be it therefore Enacted,</hi> That the said Act for securing of several Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments to <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marle,</hi> be and is hereby Repealed to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses whatsoever; and that the Proprietors of the said Lands and their Heirs and Assigns be restored to their said ancient Estates in the same manner, with the said other ancient Proprietors, their Heirs and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:201495:25"/>
            <p>If any of the <hi>ancient Proprietors,</hi> (i. e.) the Heirs of those <hi>Barbarous Rebels,</hi> (who in 1641, exceeded the sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est <hi>Turkish</hi> Cruelty) have been so thirsty as to purchase their old Estates, or any part of them, they shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised, and reinburst their purchase Mony out of some honest Gentlemans Estate, and this surely was Mony well laid out. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas,</hi> several ancient Proprietors whose Estates were seized and vested in Persons deriving a Title under the said Acts of Settlement or Explanation, have in some time after the passing the said Acts, purchased their own ancient Estates or parts thereof, from the Persons who held the same under the said Acts as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, which old Proprietors would now be restored to their said antient Estates, if they had not purchased the same. And for as much as the said ancient Proprietors or their Heirs, should receive no benefit of the said Act of Repeal, should they not be reprized for the Mony paid by them for their said ancient <hi>Estates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it therfore Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,</hi> That all and every the ancient Proprietor or Proprietors, or their Heirs, who have laid out any Sum or Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for the purchase of their own ancient Estates, or any part thereof as aforesaid, shall receive out of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon▪ stock of Reprisals, a sufficient recompence and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction▪ for the Mony laid out by him or them for the purchase of their said ancient Estate, at the rate of Ten Years purchase, any <hi>Clause, Act or Statute</hi> to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Such as that Serene Government has been pleased to mark with the names of Rebels, are tyed to a certain fix'd time for procuring Certificates of their Innocence, and Inrolling their Pardons, though at the same time the Commissioners and other Ministers may chuse whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no they will grant either, till the time (allowed) be elapsed; but in the case where the other good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Blood-suckers of 1641, their Heirs or As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:201495:26"/> are delayed in obtaining Letters Patents pursuant to the Act of Repeal, there a Certificate shall be of as great force, and bear the same Authority as Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents under the Broad Seal, as appears by what follows.</p>
            <p>And for prevention of all unnecessary Delays, and unjust Charges which can or may happen to the Subjects of this Realm, (<hi>viz. the Rebels of 1641. their Heirs and Assigns</hi>) before their full and final Setlement, <hi>Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,</hi> That where the Commissioners for Execution of the said Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, or any three or more of them, shall give any Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate under his or their Hands and Seals, to any Person or Persons, Bodies Politick or Corporate, in order to the passing any Letters Patents according to the said Act, and shall likewise return a Duplicate of such Certificate unto his Majesties Court of Exchequer at <hi>Dublin</hi> to be there enrolled, and the Person and Persons, Bodies Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick or Corporate, to whom such Certificate shall be given, shall during the space of six Months next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing the date thereof, dilligently prosecute the having and obtaining Letters Patents accordingly, but shall be thereof delayed and hindred by the neglect of any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer or Officers, that then and in such Case the several and respective Person, Bodies Politick and Corporate, to whom or in whose behalf such Certificate shall be given or granted, shall hold and enjoy the several Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suages, Mannors, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments in the several and respective Certificates mentioned and allotted according to such Estate, and under such Rent as are therein mentioned, <hi>as fully and amply to all intents and purposes, as if Letters Patents thereof had been granted and perfected according to the direction of the said former Act,</hi> any thing in this or the said former Act, or any other Law, Statute or Usage to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. That those dutiful Subjects may have no cause of complaint, see the following Clause, viz.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:201495:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas</hi> by the hardships and Oppressions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced by the said Acts of Settlement and Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, some ancient Proprietors who would have been restorable by the said Act of Repeal, have been necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to accept of Leases for Life, Lives, or Years, or Gifts in Tail, or other Conveyances of their respective Estates, and have contracted to pay some Rents, Duties, or other Reservations out of such their ancient Estates, by which acceptance of Leases, or Gifts before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and by the said Agreements to pay Rents, Duties or Reservations for the same; the said ancient Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors may be barred, or stopped, and excluded from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Restitution intended for ancient Proprietors, by the said Act of Repeal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it therefore Enacted,</hi> that the acceptance of any such Lease or Leases, Gift or Gifts intail, or other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement or Agreements upon any such account for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Rents, Duties, or other Reservation for any such their ancient respective Estate or Estates shall be no way prejudicial, or binding, or conclusive to any such ancient Proprietors, or to his or their Heirs, Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or Administrators, any thing herein, or in the said Act of Repeal to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>In a Word to render the Complyance of the Protestants (if any were so minded) altogether impossible; it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that all Letters to be granted of any Office, or Lands, shall contain a Clause, compelling the Inrolment in the Chancery in <hi>Ireland,</hi> viz. <hi>And it is further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,</hi> That all Letters Patents hereafter to be granted of any Office or Lands whatsoever, shall contain in the same Letters Patents, a Clause requiring and compelling the said Patentees to cause the said Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents to be enrolled in the Chancery of <hi>Ireland,</hi> within a time therein to be limited, and Letters Patents wherein such Clauses be omitted, are hereby declared to be utterly void and of none effect.</p>
            <p>By the subsequent Clause they gave their King a Power
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:201495:27"/> to the 1st day of <hi>Nov.</hi> 1689. to pardon, with this Restriction, that the said Letters Patents of Pardon, shall be enrolled in the Rolls Office of the Chancery in <hi>Ireland</hi> before the last of <hi>Nov.</hi> 1689. or else to be void and of none effect; a thing that was never known or whispered in <hi>England,</hi> or in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Quarters in <hi>Ireland</hi> till the Year 1690. and that the Master of the Rolls, and that obliging Attorny General of whom you have had a short Discription, page may not be hopeless of good Griest to their Mills, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that no Letters Patents of Pardon may contain above one Person: And that the Reader may be Judge of the Matter of Fact, here it begins thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided always,</hi> That if your Sacred Majesty at any time before the first day of <hi>November</hi> 1689. by Letters Patents under the Broad Seal of <hi>England</hi> residing there, or by Letters Patents under the Broad Seal of <hi>Ireland</hi> during your▪ Majesties aboad here, shall grant your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pardon or Pardons to any one or more of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons herein before mentioned, or intended to be attaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who shall return to their Duty and Loyalty, that then, and in such case, such Person and Persons so pardoned, shall be, and are hereby excepted out of this present Act, as if they never had been therein named, or thereby intended to be attainted, and shall be, and are hereby acquitted and discharged from all Attainders, Penalties and Forfeitures created or inflicted by this Act, or the said Act of Repeal, <hi>Excepting</hi> such share or proportion of their Real or Personal Estates as your Majesty shall think fit to except or reserve from them; any thing in this present Act, or in the said Act of Repeal to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided always,</hi> that every such Pardon or Pardons be pursuant to a Warrant under your Majesties privy Signet, or Sign Manual, and that no one Letters Patents of Pardon shall contain above one Person; And that all and every such Letters Patents of Pardon and Pardons shall be inrolled in the Rolls Office in your Majesties
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:201495:27"/> High Court of Chancery in this Kingdom (of <hi>Ireland</hi>) at or before the said last day of the said Month of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> or indefault thereof, to be absolutely void and of no effect, any thing herein contained to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided likewise,</hi> that if any Person or Persons so pardoned, shall at any time after the date of the said Pardon, joyn with, or aid, or assist any of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Enemies, or with any Rebels in any of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Dominions, and be thereof convicted or attainted by any due Course of Law, that then, and in such case they shall forfeit all the benefit and advantage of such Pardon, and shall be again subject and lyable to all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties and Forfeitures inflicted on them, and every of them by this or the said Act of Repeal; as if such Pardon or Pardons had never been granted; <hi>Provided always,</hi> that nothing in this Act contained shall extend, or be construed to extend to vest in your Majesty any Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, or other interest of any ancient Proprietor, who by the said Act of Repeal is to be restored to his ancient Estate, but that all such Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or Persons, and all the Right, Title and Interest are, and shall be saved, and reserved according to the true intent and meaning of the said Act, any thing in these Presents to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dublin Jan. 24th.</hi> 1689. Examined <hi>per L. Lealby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now by what's here truly Copied out of their Originals, and from the short Remarks made thereupon; I hope the Reader will not think it tedious or improper by way of Conclusion, to give a summary Account of some late Transactions in and about <hi>Dublin,</hi> and the Misery the Protestants were in, both there and in the Country; The late King's tame Submission, and truckling to the French, their Insolency, Pride and Haughtiness, as well to the Papists as Protestants, and many other Passages.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:201495:28"/>
            <p>From that time, the Lord Mayor put his witty trick on the Country People about their Corn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It was observed that the Markets were very ill furnished, and seldom Five Barrels of any kind of Grain seen on any Market Day. Then it's agreed on in their Councils to Erect publick Stores through the Kingdom, for gathering in Wheat, Malt, and all sorts of Grain, and also for Leather, Wool, Butter, Cheese, and what else they thought fit; and under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of furnishing and filling Stores, to support an Army, (as you see in the Proclamation for that end,) Seized all the visible effects of those poor Protestants that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their wings, sending such quantities of all sorts to <hi>France</hi> as the Ingrosser pleased. The late King was not the only Merchant, but under his License many Transported great quantities; as <hi>Delabody</hi> had a License for <hi>Fifteen Thousand Pound</hi> value. Many of the Dealers knowing it to be <hi>Felony</hi> to Transport Wool into <hi>France,</hi> were cautious how they dealt in that Commodity; it was hoped that some of them that were taken by King <hi>William</hi>'s Fleet, would be made Examples to deter others from falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the like Errour.</p>
            <p>Before <hi>March</hi> last, they had Seized above <hi>Thirty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Barrels</hi> of Wheat within two Miles of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and <hi>Six Thousand</hi> Barrels in the County of <hi>West-Meath,</hi> besides other sorts of Grain; and we heard that the like Methods had been put in Execution in all parts of the Kingdom under their Power. One Mr. <hi>Babe,</hi> Surveyer General, was commanded to Seise all the Malt in <hi>Dublin</hi> for the King's use, which he disobeying, as not belonging to his Office, and unwilling to Plunder his Fellow Protestants, was displaced as a Dis-affected Person, and one put in that would observe <hi>Popish Orders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Ingrossing the Corn and other Provisions, it was believed and said by some <hi>of the Popish Party,</hi> that it was to Starve all the Protestants; and some of them swore in Coffee-Houses, it would never be well with the good Catholick Subjects, till the one half of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:201495:28"/> the Protestants were Hanged and the other half Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>Some others say, that nothing should be sold out of the Stores to the Protestants, but for Gold and Silver, by which means they would certainly get it; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they have tryed many ways, yet none look'd so effectual as this, unless putting them to the Rack and their Oaths to discover what Silver or Gold they had; with which they have been long threatned, though some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence has still averted it. Flesh was sold at Six Pence a Pound, and all provisions very dear; yet there was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be had for Mony, till the Markets were abused by wheedling and foolish Proclamations.</p>
            <p>The Protestants in the Country having some foresight of the scarcity they might endure, and remembring the miseries some of them had seen, and some others had heard their Ancestors endured in 1641, thought it pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to provide good Stores of Hang'd Beef, Bacon, Dryed Fish, Pease and Beans, which by order from the Government (under the name of Seizing) was by the Souldiers plunder taken from them. Some others of them having got Brass Mony, laid it out on Wool, Hides, Butter Cheese, and Tallow, which was likewise taken from them; and when those Poor, Naked, Pillaged Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures sought redress, they were mock'd and scoft at by those that gave orders to plunder them.</p>
            <p>Such of the old Proprietors as pretended any claim to the Estates of the Absentees, they took Leases from the Commissioners for Executing the Act of <hi>Repeal;</hi> and about <hi>May</hi> last, when they were to be put in Possession, they held on, and so prevented the Sheriffs trouble.</p>
            <p>Such of the Protestants as were resolved to abide and endure the brunt of things, care was taken to frighten them away; the Government issues <hi>a secret Order</hi> to the several Lieutenants of the Counties, to turn the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> out of such Estates as the Papists had any claim to, and put them in, who were sure would not let the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:201495:29"/> carry away one Pennyworth of their Goods, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as some satisfaction for the mean profits. Thus they dealt with the Lord Primate (<hi>Boyl,</hi>) who lost about Ten Thousand Pound value in the furniture of his House at <hi>Blessington,</hi> and Killed all the Deer in his Park, though the Flesh at that time was of no use; this was not so much to be admired, when by authority under the Government, they Destroyed all the Deer in <hi>Rafernum</hi> Park, and in the Park by <hi>Chappell-Izzard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if yet some of the Protestants remained on their Estates, to which those old Proprietors could make no Claim, on those the Lieutenants by the aforesaid Order might quarter Soldiers at discretion, which they did to the great grief of those Gentlemen, who as long as they could, gave free Quarters to such Numbers as were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on them; but not being able to endure this Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and the abuses put on themselves, Wives and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, were forced to fly with their Lives. And this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded even the <hi>French</hi> Dragooning; thus to be forced to abandon their fair Buildings, Orchards, and other Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, was more untollerable, than the loss of what was taken from them before, hoping in time to recover some of their Estates and other Losses, but never their Improvements; which those Ruffians (knowing their Reign to be but short) designedly defaced, rooted up, burnt and destroyed, and which had been brought to yield profit as well as pleasure by great Charge and Industry, since the Settlement after 1641. Who would not be afflicted thus to be turned out, to make room for his Cow-boy or Swine-Herd, and see them decide his Mansion House into Seven or Eight several Dwellings, for those Brutes whose Fore-Fathers never lay on any other or better Bed than a few green Rushes, or a little Straw, and after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner have they divided that noble Building of <hi>Eyres-Court</hi> in the County of <hi>Gallway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Protestants being persecuted from Place to Place in the Country, at length fled to <hi>Dublin,</hi> where indeed to say
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:201495:29"/> truth, the Protestant Citizens have been so liberal, both to the Protestant Prisoners, and those that were not, that it is to be admired how their Purses held out; at one Collection on a Sabbath day, it was usual to receive Fifty or Sixty Pound, and had it not been for such large Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, it had gone hard with the Country Gentry, who had not received any Rent from <hi>May</hi> 1688, and always Improving their Estates, kept but little Money by them, which they were forced to spend in the defence of Law Suits, and other vexatious troubles put on them by the Implacable <hi>Papists;</hi> and those that after all had saved some in considerable Sum, which though never so thriftily mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, yet by the scarcity and dearness of things in <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> it was soon spent, and thence they became greater Objects, as being really in a worse condition than the meaner sort, who could work for Victuals; however as soon as their Poverty was made known, (which was not before they had almost perished,) there was a competent Dividend of the publick Collection sent by a private hand; and thus by the mutual sense and Fellow-feeling of our Distresses, we supported one another.</p>
            <p>That Order sent to the Lieutenants of the several Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to quarter Men and Horses at Discretion on the Protestants, was never shew'd to any of us, so that we could never come by a Copy of it; but yet they freely told us the Contents, and put them in Execution, with all the severity imaginable, to our great Grief and Loss never to be repaired.</p>
            <p>By the late King's being in Possession of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis of the Kingdom, gained great credit with <hi>France,</hi> though it has been used as if designed for Flames, when no longer tenable by the late King and his Adherents; Fifty Thousand Pounds would not Repair the Damage done to the Buildings thereof before <hi>March</hi> last; without opening of a Gate or Door, one might have walked, nay almost rid from one end to the other of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:201495:30"/>
            <p>A brisk Trade was kept up with the <hi>French,</hi> who sent great quantities of Fruit, Wine, Brandy, Hops, Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, and other gross Commodities; for which they carried away the best that was in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as Butter, Cheese, Wooll, raw Hides and Tallow; the late King released 11 <hi>l. 10 s.</hi> Imposition on every Tun of Wine, and this was done in favour of his Army, who before paid Two Shillings a Quart, and then but one.</p>
            <p>The <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> when Sir <hi>Clously Shovel</hi> appeared before <hi>Dublin</hi> with the Fleet under his Command, great quantities of the Protestants Goods being Seized, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ships Loaded, and a Loading with them, the late King and his Crew were under terrible apprehensions at first, believing that some Land-Men would be sent from the Ships to Reduce <hi>Dublin,</hi> but seeing they only attack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Ships in the Pool, and fearing they might come into the Harbour where the Loaded Ships lay, all Hands were imployed to unload; but Sir <hi>Clously</hi> going off with a smaller Prise than was expected, and the Coast being clear, all Hands were again made use of to Load all the Ships in the Harbour with the Protestants Goods; which being done, they set Sail under the Convoy of the late King's whole Fleet, consisting of Four Ships, one of Eighteen Guns, one of Sixteen, one of Twelve Guns, and a <hi>French</hi> Privateer. That shew made by Sir <hi>Clously,</hi> had like to have been fatal to the Protestants, whose Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance being somewhat chearful, immediately it was proclaimed Death to a <hi>Protestant</hi> found out of Doors; on some it fell heavily, as upon a Gentleman of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance being on a Visit among some Relations in the Inns beyond the Bridge, not knowing the danger, going homeward, was stopp'd on <hi>Essex</hi> Bridge, receiving a Cut above Seven Inches long on his Head, which for Two Years before, aked most violently, but to his great ease, the same pain has not visited him since his Recovery. And what were we to have in exchange for all those choice Commodities? Arms and Ammunition to Murder us; and indeed we could
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:201495:30"/> expect no other, that being the Exchange agreed upon before-hand.</p>
            <p>Silver and Gold became one of the greatest and best Commodities in <hi>Dublin;</hi> between Buyer and Seller, a <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea</hi> before <hi>May</hi> last was sold at 3 <hi>l. 10 s.</hi> and an Ounce of Silver at Three Crowns of Brass Mony, and so propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable for other quantities of Gold and Silver. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>French</hi> brought great quantities of Brass and Copper, yet it was not enough; so that they began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Weights of what was already Coined, by melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it down, and making it less in the new Coin; the value of Brass Mony fell daily, before <hi>March</hi> Six Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thousand Pounds was Coined.</p>
            <p>The Mint has been of late altogether managed by Protestants; some time since there being Papists in one branch, were discovered to cheat above Five Hundred Pound a Week in the Six-pences, for which they were slightly punished, and so turned off; which had been Death in a Protestant. And not only in this, but in all other common ordinary Affairs, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants were forced to contrive things for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists.</p>
            <p>The necessary Charge of the Army, came to Eleven Hundred Thousand Pound <hi>per Annum,</hi> and the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue of the Kingdom never came to above Three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thirty Two Thousand Pounds <hi>per Annum;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if the late King had been pay'd all he could pretend to, the Twenty Thousand Pounds Subsidy would not half sustain'd his Army; so that of necessity there must have been Coined Yearly, Six Hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Pounds in Brass Mony, which having no way to circulate, must be so much Loss to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and in short time come to nothing. But to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this, he offered to pledge or pawn his Quit-Rent, for Brass Mony, at Six <hi>per Cent;</hi> but no body has trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:201495:31"/>
            <p>Whilst this Brass Mony past, it was of extraordinary benefit to the Distressed Protestants, all that had it, were ready to Lend those that wanted, otherwise some Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds would have perished, that through meer shame could not discover their condition, to receive of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Charity.</p>
            <p>Of late the Protestants could not come by a bit of Bread, but what they purchased at triple rates from the Soldiers, a Dozen or Twenty of them being placed about every Bakers House to prevent the <hi>Protestants</hi> from coming by any; of which cruel dealings, the late King being informed, he answered that his Army must not want Bread whosoever did; this was some of his tenderness to his Protestant Subjects; but they made one shift or other to get it till the <hi>French</hi> came, and I fear from thence, many were Starved for want of Bread.</p>
            <p>The Protestant Tradesmen were all Imployed, though they had rather sate Idle, being ill payed for their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and that in Brass Mony, which they freely gave to their Fellow Sufferers that wanted most.</p>
            <p>From the whole, it is easy to observe the Case of the Protestants to be very deplorable, being Robbed and Plundered of all they had in the World, enslaved and subjected to those they hated and despised. And although the late King or his Army, could not subsist one day without the <hi>Protestants,</hi> yet were they nevertheless abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, slighted, opprest, and had more barbarous usage than could been expected from <hi>Algereens;</hi> we were sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible they only spared our Lives whilst serviceable to them, and afterwards our certain Destruction was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed: In the mean time, the Protestants were forced to strengthen and support their Enemies.</p>
            <p>If the Protestant Butchers, Brewers, Bakers, Clothiers, Weavers, Taylors, Shooe-makers, Hat-makers, Smiths, Carpenters, and other Artizens, had been removed from
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:201495:31"/> them, they could not have had Meat, Bread or Drink, Cloaths to wear, nor Carts to carry Provision, Arms or Ammunition into▪ the Fields; nor would the late King had a Mint, Brass or Copper to Coin in it: so that they had suspended all thoughts of turning out the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, as it was often moved in their Councils. The Governour▪ <hi>Luttorel</hi> told the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador, that if the Protestants were turned out of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the Papists must quit it; and when they quitted <hi>Dublin,</hi> they must quit <hi>Ireland.</hi> It was the City that almost maintained and supported the late King's Army last Winter, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to quarter above Twenty Thousand Men at one time: And therefore it was no wonder they were unwilling to part with such a Place. But however the matter went, they were resolved as soon as King <hi>William</hi> took the Field, to confine all the Protestants to the Churches, Hospitals and Goals, which it seems they did; and which was their common practice on every slight Alarm.</p>
            <p>About the Twelfth of <hi>March</hi> last, the <hi>French</hi> Fleet consisting of about Forty Men of War, and about Sixty Tenders and others, came into <hi>Cork</hi> Harbour, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Five Thousand <hi>French</hi> Land-men; for which as you have heard, as many of the Brave Old Heroick Bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trotters were to be sent to the <hi>French</hi> King; but many of them according to their usual custom run away, in the place of whom many Protestants were Pressed for that Service to their great grief. It was then discoursed, that as soon as they returned to <hi>France,</hi> an Additional Fleet would Join them, and that they intended to bring Ten Thousand Land Men with them for the late Kin'gs Service; which doubtless is the Fleet on our Coasts. Some of the Nobility about the late King, discoursing of the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> said they to him, <hi>Sir, Is not the</hi> French <hi>Fleet in great danger to be met with by the</hi> English; to which he Replied, <hi>That he during his time, had taken
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:201495:32"/> care that the English should not have any great strength by Sea; and now to equip and fit out a Fleet, would be tedious, besides the expences; and that he did not doubt but the French would master them;</hi> the French had not been well landed at <hi>Cork</hi> when some pestilent Distemper carryed off above five hundred of them, they soon began to murmur, saying, They were promised great Matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they left <hi>France,</hi> of which, since their coming they saw but small appearance, about three Months Pay in Silver and Gold was sent with them from <hi>France,</hi> which was of a very course Metal, and a third part less in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsick Value, than as it formerly past in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three Battalions of the French marched towards <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> appointed as General <hi>Lauzuns</hi> Guards; the late King having promised his Guardian (<hi>i. e.</hi>) the French King, that the French General should have the possession of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and of all the places of any Strength in <hi>Ireland;</hi> accordingly on the the 3d of <hi>May Lauzun</hi> sent to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor <hi>Lutterel</hi> to deliver the Keys of the City and Castle, to whom <hi>Lutterel</hi> answered, he would first acquaint the King, who forthwith accompanied the Lord Mayor and Aldermen to address the King, telling him they had thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ventur'd their Lives and Fortunes in his Defence, and therefore hoped he would not still confide in them to govern <hi>Dublin,</hi> and would not make them absolute Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the French, to whom he reply'd, That he had engaged, and past his Word to his Brother <hi>Lewis,</hi> that <hi>Lauzun</hi> should have the Government of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and could not recede from it; thereupon the Keys of the City was delivered, but the <hi>French</hi> would not mount the Guards till they had likewise the Keys of the Castle, which being also comply'd with, on the fourth of <hi>May,</hi> the French possest themselves of City and Castle, swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had no King but <hi>Lewis,</hi> nor would they obey any other, and under him their General <hi>Lauzun:</hi> from thence they grew so very Rude and Insolent, not only
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:201495:32"/> to Protestants, but to Papists, that the later grew mighty melancholy and dejected, frequently complaining to their King, who had no power to help himself or them, having by his degenerate and mean Spirit truckl'd his Authority, and became subject to the power of <hi>France,</hi> and contented himself to be nominal King.</p>
            <p>Of which, the better and more sober sort of Papists were sensible (foreseeing a suddain change of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) could never be perswaded to take on them the least Office or Employment under him, even that of Constable, but resolved to lay hold on the first Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and throw themselves at the Mercy of our most Gracious King, which ere now they have had a good opportunity to embrace.</p>
            <p>And though how ill soever the Irish Papists resented the Insolence of the French, yet the Majority were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to bear with all rather than by expressing their inward dislike or discontent, giving encouragement to the Protestants, to hope for any advantage that might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen from Discords among Papists, and therefore carest and treated the French, who called them ten thousand Cowards, and said, they were beaten by a Priest and a few Boys, meaning that valiant Colonel <hi>Walker,</hi> and those matchless Hero's that suffer'd with him.</p>
            <p>There being above ten thousand Protestant Men in <hi>Dublin</hi> able to bear Arms, besides Women and Children, and being barr'd of the liberty of the Markets by the French, who would not sell Bread to the Protestants as the Irish Papist Soldiers did; it is a Miracle if thousands the Protestants had not perished.</p>
            <p>The French as they past by any of our Clergy, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened them sadly; on which the Clergy held frequent Consultations how to secure themselves, and deliver'd their poor Flocks from the daily Threats and Menaces of the French Vultures.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:201495:33"/>
            <p>It was moved that the Clergy should disguise them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in Frieze Coats, not finding it probable to escape the then impending Dangers in their Gowns; this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was rejected by the Majority, and still depending on his Protection, who stills the Winds, and the raging of the Seas.</p>
            <p>The French had not been two days in <hi>Dublin</hi> when they murdered two or three Protestant Clothiers, in a part of the City called the <hi>Comb;</hi> for that great Crime of protecting their Wives from being made Prostitutes to the French, of which Inhuman Act no notice was ever taken, more than if two Dogs had been, shot. About the same time some of them took a Country-Maid that came to Market with her Father, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floured her in the open Street at Noon-day. Many such barbarous pieces of Villany has been perpetrated by those Blood-suckers, whose continual Practice was in all Parts of the World where they have been, to burn and demolish such Places as were not tenable by them; and so they moved in their Councils, that that famous City of <hi>Dublin</hi> should be dealt with; first to shut up the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants in the Churches and Hospitals, and then if they lost the day, to set Fire to all, whereby not only the City, but the Protestants also should be destroyed; whereupon the Irish City Papists, and those of the Army apply'd themselves to their King, and told him they should suffer in that Expedition, as well as the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants; and that they would not draw a Sword in his Defence, unless all thoughts of burning the City were set aside, and declared that as soon as they saw or heard of any appearance of Fire, they would fly from his Service and submit to King <hi>Williams</hi> Mercy, of which, now they have had a good Experiment, and we hope to have that account of those usurping, intruding Ruffians, which <hi>Count D'avaux</hi> prophesied at the landing of General <hi>Lauzun</hi> and the French; said <hi>D'avaux</hi> to <hi>Lauzun,</hi> You are come
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:201495:33"/> to be a Sacrifice for a poor spirited and cowardly People, whose Souldiers will never Fight, and whose Officers would never observe Orders, and therefore they would meet with the same Fate his Masters Army met with at the Siege of <hi>Candia,</hi> that is, to be wasted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, those that came to relieve not standing by them; and thus we see the wonderful Work of God (who has protected the Protestants in <hi>Dublin</hi>) delivered them from <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his Hosts on the fourth day of this Instant <hi>July.</hi> Our gracious Deliverer King <hi>William,</hi> and his Royal Consort Queen <hi>Mary</hi> were proclaimed KING and QUEEN in <hi>Dublin,</hi> by the command, and in the presence of his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> without any great loss on our side, and with wonderful satisfaction, and unexpressible Joy to those poor Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, who were upon the same Day released from their Bondage.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:201495:34"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE History of the Wars in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Two Parts; by <hi>Richard Cox,</hi> Esq; Attendant on King <hi>William</hi> in this Expedition: Published by Authority. Printed for <hi>Joseph Watts,</hi> at the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</p>
            <p>A List of Persons Attainted by the Late King <hi>James</hi> and their Estates Confiscated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavell,</hi> and <hi>Joseph Watts,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</p>
            <p>The Present Settlement Vindicated, and the late Misgovernment proved by Sir <hi>J. Temple.</hi> Printed for <hi>Joseph Watts</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>